<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new account of the present condition of the Turkish affairs, with the causes of the decay of the Ottoman power; of their wars with the present emperor, &amp;c, and the facility the Christian princes now have of retaking Constantinople, according to a prophecy of the Turks themselves. Together with several notable remarks upon the late insolence of the army; of their deposing Mahomet IV. (who had reigned eight and forty years) and setting his younger brother in his seat. To which is prefixed, the effigies of this new emperor, Solyman the Third. By a person of quality, who long resided amongst them, and is lately returned home</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2921A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899271</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899271</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152938</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152938)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2334:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new account of the present condition of the Turkish affairs, with the causes of the decay of the Ottoman power; of their wars with the present emperor, &amp;c, and the facility the Christian princes now have of retaking Constantinople, according to a prophecy of the Turks themselves. Together with several notable remarks upon the late insolence of the army; of their deposing Mahomet IV. (who had reigned eight and forty years) and setting his younger brother in his seat. To which is prefixed, the effigies of this new emperor, Solyman the Third. By a person of quality, who long resided amongst them, and is lately returned home</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
                  <author>Sturt, John, 1658-1730, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 190 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVIII. [1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Frontis. portrait (plate) engraved and signed: I. Sturt sculp:.</note>
                  <note>ICN copy (reel 2334) missing plate.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  Court and courtiers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:1"/>
            <p>A NEW ACCOUNT Of the preſent Condition of the <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKISH</hi> Affairs, With the Cauſes of the Decay of the <hi>OTTOMAN</hi> POWER; Of their Wars with the preſent Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> And the Facility the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes now have of retaking <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> according to a Prophecy of the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>Together with ſeveral Notable Remarks upon the late Inſolence of the Army; of their depoſing <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. (who had Reigned Eight and forty Years) and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his <hi>younger</hi> Brother in his Seat.</p>
            <p>To which is prefixed, the <hi>Effigies</hi> of this <hi>New</hi> Emperor, <hi>Solyman</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p>By a Perſon of Quality, who long reſided amongſt them, and is lately returned Home.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO HIS SERENE HIGHNESS, THE GREAT DUKE OF TUSCANY.</head>
            <byline>By the Sieur <hi>Du Vignau,</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador to the <hi>Port, &amp;c.</hi> A. D. 1687/8.</byline>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IMagining my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to give an Account to the Publick,
<pb facs="tcp:152938:4"/> of whatever I could learn of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Policy, and different Manners of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, during Nine Years Abode at <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and ſeveral other Parts of their Empire, which I have paſs'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; I have therefore laid hold on this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture of their Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal, to ſhew the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> World, that this great <hi>Coloſs,</hi> which has been hitherto reſpected
<pb facs="tcp:152938:4"/> as Impregnable, ſtands on Foundations eaſily mov'd and overthrown, as ſubſiſting by ſuch Prejudices, and falſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, as have been made of its Greatneſs.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge, <hi>my Lord,</hi> that this Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation might paſs for a <hi>Chimera,</hi> had it come into my Head, whilſt <hi>Mahomet</hi> the <hi>Conqueror, Selim</hi> II. and <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the <hi>Magnificent,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual'd
<pb facs="tcp:152938:5"/> the Number of their Victories to that of their Enterpriſes; and whilſt Fortune made Kingdoms and Empires ſtoop to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Yoke. But theſe vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Conquerors, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſo Redoutable, are only heard of now by the ſorry Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a piteous Defence; and I do not doubt, but every body will enter into the Sentiments which I have of the
<pb facs="tcp:152938:5"/> Weakneſs of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, eſpecially in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring what they ſee, with what I ſhall ſay: Whence they will judge, that a Power, which, maugre the Fierceneſs of its firſt Maxims, ſtoops to ſuch ſupplicating Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions for Peace, is not ſuch as has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deſcrib'd, and is only capable of ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a War, to bring grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Honour to thoſe who attack Her.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:6"/>
            <p>What Occaſion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I might have of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering my ſelf, <hi>my Lord,</hi> that this Reflection will diſpoſe Mens Minds to accept of my Deſign, yet I ſhall fear to expoſe my ſelf to the Publick, ſhould <hi>your ſerene High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> refuſe the Grace of bringing it into the World under the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of your great Name.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:6"/>
            <p>In effect, <hi>my Lord,</hi> under whoſe more effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious and happy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, can I ſhelter it from the Severity of Mens Cenſures, than in a Family where ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Princes have always appeared, and where the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt the Deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Grandure of the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> has ſignaliz'd it ſelf by ſo many he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Actions on Sea
<pb facs="tcp:152938:7"/> and Land, making con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual War againſt them, for the Glory and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Religion, the Benefit of Commerce, and Safety of <hi>Italy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let a Man run over the Coaſts of <hi>Africk,</hi> the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> the <hi>Archipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lago, Adriatic</hi> Sea, the Gulfs, Havens, and all the Iſles of the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean,</hi> and is there any Part which is not Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Exploits, and
<pb facs="tcp:152938:7"/> great Actions, which the Valour of Princes, or Captains of the Auguſt Houſe of the <hi>Medici's,</hi> have there perform'd?</p>
            <p>I ſhall leave this <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium</hi> to the Juſtice and Fidelity of Hiſtory, which will be far from forgetting one of her moſt precious Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the glorious Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of whatever your <hi>ſerene Highneſs</hi> does eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, and whatever
<pb facs="tcp:152938:8"/> your Illuſtrious Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors have done in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Name, againſt the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan</hi> Superſtitions. I leave to publick Fame, the care of finding more eloquent Expreſſions, and more proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than mine can be, to the Merit and Majeſty of ſo Auguſt a Subject; whilſt following my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, of entering into the <hi>Penetralia</hi> of the Government of the
<pb facs="tcp:152938:8"/> 
               <hi>Port,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to make it known, that its Greatneſs ſubſiſts on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the Prejudices of thoſe who never truly underſtood it.</p>
            <p>This is indeed a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Deſign, but it's a Deſign, <hi>my Lord,</hi> which does not aſtoniſh me, and which will meet with Applauſes, even amongſt thoſe who take Pleaſure in cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all Mens Works,
<pb facs="tcp:152938:9"/> when it ſhall be ſeen, I have produced this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Patronage of one of the moſt glorious Princes of the World, to whom I eſteem it my greateſt Glory to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A moſt Humble and devoted Servant, <hi>Du Vignau.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:9"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT'S well known, how for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er has made it ſelf to all the Earth, and what a great Part of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> groans under the Yoke of its Tyranny. The Terror of its Arms had taken ſuch deep Root, that there ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no preſent Means of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but by Prayers and Tears, the Churches Weapons. But
<pb facs="tcp:152938:10"/> it's now time to ſhew the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs of this Fear, by ſerious Reflections on the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture of Affairs, and by juſt and well grounded Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, which are ſufficient to diſcover perfectly the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Weakneſs of a Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niation ſo malign and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Name.</p>
            <p>If we conſider its Original, we ſhall find, according to the Relation of moſt Writers, that it's owing to a deform'd Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which not having the means of encreaſing, or ſubſiſting in the vaſt Campaigns of <hi>Turco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania,</hi> where it took its Birth, has extended its ſelf with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitation in the Three beſt
<pb facs="tcp:152938:10"/> Parts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, where it has form'd its Greatneſs, of as many Empires, Kingdoms and Principalities, as there are Relations in Hiſtory. It has moreover reduced the ſo great Diverſity of Laws, Cuſtoms and Sciences, which reigned in the Countries of its Conqueſts, almoſt all to one certain Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a Soveraign Will and Abſolute Power, ſuch as they bragg of their acknowledging in God, to the Excluſion of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Power has made it ſelf ſo conſiderable, both by Sea and Land, that he who conſiders it in the groſs, muſt needs be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted at it. It moreover
<pb facs="tcp:152938:11"/> ſeems, that in all which has been hitherto written on this Subject, there's no one has da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to undeceive Mens falſe Imaginations, but rather to heighten and encreaſe them; and rather, to entertain the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with what they take Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to believe, than to inform them of what they be deſirous to know.</p>
            <p>And, as we cannot better undeceive Mens Minds, and obliterate the ſtrong Impreſſions which are had of a thing, than by Facts, and Inſtances of the contrary; I ſhall therefore in the Courſe of this Relation, lay down nothing, but what ſhall be grounded on ſenſible Proofs,
<pb facs="tcp:152938:11"/> eſpecially on what has paſs'd in theſe latter times, and what actually happens, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> and his Neighbours, but in the <hi>Grand seignior</hi>'s own Armies; whoſe Inſolence has aſpired as high as his Throne, to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of him, and ſetting his younger Brother in his Seat; Whence it will appear without any Diſguiſe, that there needs no Miracle, for the effecting thoſe things which depend wholly on our ſelves, and are in our own Power.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="lists_of_Turkish_and_English_rulers">
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:12"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the <hi>Turkiſh Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperors</hi> from their firſt Original, and of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary with them.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Turkiſh Kings.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Kings of <hi>England</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="3">1. Othoman, Firſt King of the <hi>Turks,</hi> began his Reign <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1300.</cell>
                     <cell>Edward I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Edward II.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Edward III.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Orchanes.</cell>
                     <cell>Edward III.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">3. Amurath. I.</cell>
                     <cell>Edward III.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Richard II.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">4. Bajazet. I.</cell>
                     <cell>Richard II.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. Iſa Zebelis</cell>
                     <cell>Henry IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. Solyman I.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. Muſa.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">8. Mahomet I.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry V.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">9. Amurath II.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry V.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry VI.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb facs="tcp:152938:12"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Turkiſh Emperors.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Kings of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">1. Mahomet II. who taking <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> was made Emperor of the <hi>Eaſt May</hi> 29th. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1453.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry VI.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Edward IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="5">2. Bajazet II.</cell>
                     <cell>Edward IV.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Edward V.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Richard III.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry VII.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henry VIII.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. Selymus I.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry VIII.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="4">4. Solyman II.</cell>
                     <cell>Henry VIII.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Edward VI.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Q. Mary.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Q. Eliz.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. Selymus II.</cell>
                     <cell>Q. Eliz.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. Amurath III.</cell>
                     <cell>Q. Eliz.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. Mahomet III.</cell>
                     <cell>Q. Eliz.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. Achmat.</cell>
                     <cell>James I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9. Muſtapha.</cell>
                     <cell>James I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. Oſman.</cell>
                     <cell>James I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſtapha again</cell>
                     <cell>James I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11. Amurath IV.</cell>
                     <cell>Charles I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12. Ibrahim.</cell>
                     <cell>Charles I.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152938:13"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">13. Mahomet IV.</cell>
                     <cell>Charles II.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>James II.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14. Solyman III. whom the Army (after their ill Succeſs this laſt Campaign) ſeated in the Throne, having firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his elder Brother, <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. who had reigned 48 Years.</cell>
                     <cell>James II.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:13"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. OF the Strength and Weakneſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> in general. <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. Of the Two Principal Means of the Growth of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power. With an Hiſtorical Abridgment of the Ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of the <hi>Turks,</hi> from which <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> never drew any Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. Several other Reaſons of the Encreaſe of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power, and particular Obſervations on the Laſt War, with
<pb facs="tcp:152938:14"/> the <hi>Emperor,</hi> the <hi>Venetians, Poles,</hi> and <hi>Moſcovites. pag.</hi> 54.</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. Of the principal Cauſes of the Decay of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power, with a Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Paſſage of the <hi>Dardanello's,</hi> and a Relation of the Facility the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes have at preſent of retaking <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople. pag.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. Proofs of the laſt Weakneſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> at Sea, with a Relation of the Affair at <hi>Chio. pag.</hi> 129.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. Some Politick Reflections on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ill Condition of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Affairs, ſince the raiſing the Siege of <hi>Vienna. p.</hi> 151.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. A Recapitulation of ſeveral Reaſons of the approacking Overthrow of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire: With ſeveral Remarks upon the late Revolutions at <hi>Conſtantinople. pag.</hi> 180.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152938:14"/>
            <head>THE PRESENT STATE OF THE <hi>OTTOMAN POWER:</hi> With the CAUSES OF ITS ENCREASE and DECAY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of the Strength and Weakneſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> in General.</head>
               <p>THE Reſt which the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire has almoſt time out of Mind enjoy'd on the ſide of <hi>Perſia,</hi> by reaſon of the effeminate, and unwarlike Humor of the <hi>Sophies,</hi> eſpecially ſince <hi>Sultan Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi> retook from them the important
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152938:15"/> and famous City of <hi>Bagdat</hi> or <hi>Babylon;</hi> has given her the Opportunity of bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all her Forces againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and extending them both by Sea and Land. <hi>Syria, Paleſtine, Aegypt, Aſia minor,</hi> the Two Empires of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> and <hi>Trebizond,</hi> the Coaſt of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> all the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Part of the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> the whole Coaſt of <hi>Africk, Greece, Hungary, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orgia, leſſer Tartary,</hi> and the beſt Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Poland;</hi> are Proofs as convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, as coſtly to <hi>Chriſt endom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if on one hand it has appeared Great, Majeſtical and Formidable, and is maintain'd by ſeveral Troops always in a readineſs, by their blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Emperor, and by a great Number of malign, and induſtrious Conſtitutions, which have conduc'd to ſo terrible an Aggrandiſement, and rendred it to this preſent Invincible; there will be on the other part, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Defects, as will be of themſelves capable of overthrowing and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
               <p>It's in the Firſt manner, whereby the <hi>Turk</hi> has ever attackt the Princes his Neighbors, and aſtoniſht them by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152938:15"/> boldneſs of his Enterpriſes. He has always been the Aggreſſor, even to the Prejudice of Treaties, ſurprizing his Enemies with numerous Armies; whilſt he has had no regard to the inward Parts of his Empire, which he has ſtript and reduc'd to extream Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by depriving it of the greateſt and beſt part of the People, to gather its Forces to the out-Parts and Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers.</p>
               <p>Moſt Strangers dazled with the greatneſs of this Empire, have never truly known the Weak Sides of it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying themſelves only to the outward Appearance, without penetrating to the Bottom. But, to clear up the Truth, we are to conſider in what manner the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Policy has extended to Exceſs, the Maxim of not letting its Subjects be too Rich, to avoid Softneſs, and all other Accidents thereunto belonging.</p>
               <p>The People, which is the laſt of the <hi>Three</hi> Orders or Eſtates of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, is tyranniz'd over by the <hi>Two</hi> others, which is the <hi>Military,</hi> and that of the <hi>Law.</hi> They are almoſt beggar'd, and employ'd in the vileſt and meaneſt Services; and the Tyranny goes ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152938:16"/> far, that the Miniſtry of Religion and Juſtice (of which the <hi>Second</hi> Rank or Order conſiſts) ſerves for a means to the continual and incredible Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are exercis'd by the <hi>Firſt,</hi> which is the <hi>Military,</hi> againſt the <hi>Third;</hi> which, when it ſhould compoſe the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Empire, is in a manner loſt, and every day manifeſtly decaying.</p>
               <p>It's a radicated Miſchief, and as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as the Original of the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> That the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperors have not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to conquer with Facility ſo vaſt an Extent of Land, but by entirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the People, as faſt as they ſubdued them. This Deſtruction was authoris'd by them of the <hi>Law,</hi> who have continued to be the Miniſters of it; and 'twas executed by the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, commanded by the <hi>Grand Seigniors</hi> themſelves, whoſe <hi>Vizirs</hi> were the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eutenants, and the <hi>Baſſa's</hi> fill'd the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Offices.</p>
               <p>All the Officers which apply'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Execution of theſe great Deſigns, and the purſuit of ſo many Conqueſts, ſhar'd the Profits and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. And if it be true, that this Diſtribution of Military Dignities and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152938:16"/> Governments, is now no other than a kind of Rent or Farming, which falls on the People; hence may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured, what will become in the End of this <hi>Third</hi> Eſtate, which the Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al People continue to deſolate, by a Cuſtom to which all contribute with ſuch Force and Violence, that even the very <hi>Janizaries,</hi> which are taken from amongſt the People, are weakned and deſtroy'd every Day, in ruining it.</p>
               <p>We may add to this ill Conduct, the Application of the latter <hi>Sultans</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this <hi>Militia,</hi> or at leaſt to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh its Authority, and overthrow the <hi>Baſſa's</hi> and other Officers; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways falling on the People, ſhews, that even the Head, as well, as the reſt, who are the Members of the Empire, labour at their Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>The People have ſcarcely any part in the Privileges or Honours. The Commerce which ſhould belong to them in great Towns, is divided by the Souldiers, and eſpecially by the <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries,</hi> who ſet up for Merchants at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> They do the ſame in other Places of their Abode, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over with more Impunity, as well as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152938:17"/> in their Courſes and Paſſages; entring into Gardens, to take the Fruits, and what they find there, for nothing, or at a pitiful Price, they ſell at an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Rate, in Towns, Burghs and Villages, to the Excluſion of other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom they hinder by their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or Addreſs, from concerning themſelves. How little ſoever their Traffick is, they draw thence a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Gain, becauſe they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from all the Charges and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, which are laid on the Lands and People; and have Bread, Meat, a Veſt, and a Turbant as a Gift, beſides their Pay.</p>
               <p>Hence is ſeen, that the People is the Patient, on which the <hi>Military</hi> State works; and 'twill be granted, that that of the <hi>Law,</hi> no leſs oppreſſes them, by authorizing the Injuſtices of the <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> and other Officers, who pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe incredible Extortions. Theſe are the principal Cauſes, which have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated, and reduced into Solitude, the greateſt Part of this Empire. If in theſe latter times, the <hi>Sultans</hi> have extended conſiderably their Limits, by the Conqueſt of ſeveral Provinces;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152938:17"/> this Augmentation has not been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to make amends for the Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of one Third of the People, and their Habitations; which is viſible by the Regiſters of Chancery of the Two <hi>Cadileskiers</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> who are the Two chief Judges of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. The <hi>Cadiliks,</hi> or Jurisdictions of the <hi>Firſt,</hi> were reduced before the preſent War, to Three hundred and ten, from more than Five hundred, which they were at firſt; and thoſe of the <hi>Second,</hi> are not more than Four hundred and thirty, inſtead of about Seven hundred. Whence may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that the Troops of the <hi>Baſſa's, Timars,</hi> and others, are diminiſhed proportionably, and even farther, by the Diminution and Ruin of ſeveral Places, which contributed to their Subſiſtence.</p>
               <p>Whence may be inferr'd, that the laſt Conqueſts of theſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> have yielded no other Advantage, than the hiding from the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Weakneſs, and the Miſery of <hi>Turky;</hi> which, in fine, begins to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it ſelf, and that the Efforts which they have uſed for this, have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152938:18"/> only ſerv'd to augment the Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the inward Parts of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
               <p>Whatever there is of Augmentation and Greatneſs, in the Center and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, ſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give further Proof of its Ruine and Decay. And, if it be almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to believe the great Number there are of Towns, Burghs, and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, where there remains only bare Walls, and deſolate Houſes, wherein no Body inhabits; one may moreover conſider, how many Burghs about <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> are form'd on the Sides of the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Boſphorus,</hi> and the <hi>White Sea.</hi> Every day new Buildings are there raiſed: The People who are here at preſent, far ſurpaſs the ancient Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, who inhabited it before; and this Concourſe proceeds from the great Quantity of People, who flying the Perſecutions in the Provinces, find only Eaſe and Security in the Vicinity of their Emperor.</p>
               <p>Abandoning as they do, againſt their Wills, the Country of their Birth, 'tis eaſy to judge by what Violence they are conſtrain'd to it. And, becauſe this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152938:18"/> Tyranny ſtill continues, as may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by the Iſles which are almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated, and by the Deſerts, and Ruins on the main Land; it's certain, that the Neighbourhood of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> would ariſe into a Province on lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Spaces of Ground, and on Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains rough and barren enough, had not the Imperial Edicts ſometimes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged theſe new Inhabitants, to return to their own Countries. The Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent is alſo practiſed in reſpect of thoſe, who have left their Country after they have been written in the Book of Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to make them contribute to the Charges of their Compatriots, when theſe require it; and many conſent, and pay moreover the Impoſitions on their new Habitations, rather than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into their Country. All theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who fill'd conſiderable Provinces, and the fartheſt diſtant of the Empire, being driven thence by the Violence and Tyranny of the Government, run to the Borders of great Towns, and eſpecially of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and leave all theſe Countries, which were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore the richeſt, and moſt abounding, deſart, and abandoned.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152938:19"/>
               <p>What I now come from ſaying, may ſerve as a general Idea of the Strength and Weakneſs of the <hi>Ottomans.</hi> But to make a more exact Deſcription, 'twill be neceſſary to inſiſt on Two principal Cauſes, which ſeem the moſt natural Foundation of this Dominion, which has extended it ſelf ſo far. We ſhall afterwards exhibit ſeveral others, which will appear no leſs, to be thoſe of its Ruine and Decay; and come to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtances, both of Sea and Land; by which having prov'd the Weakneſs of this Empire, we ſhall undeceive Mens Minds in their favourable Precon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152938:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the Two Principal Means of the Growth of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power. With an Hiſtorical A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the Ancient Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the <hi>Turks,</hi> from which <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> never drew any Advantage.</head>
               <p>THE Diſtributions and Share of the Conqueſts, which the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and <hi>Turkiſh Militia</hi> received from the Firſt <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperors in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their Progreſs; has oblig'd them to conſider the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> who granted them thoſe Favours, not only as their Benefactor, but alſo as him who drew them from Nothing, and out of Deſarts, to diſtribute to them the Grandures and Riches of the moſt plentiful Countries, as faſt as they made him the Maſter of them. This Hope flattered them in ſuch ſort, as to oblige them to fear no Dangers and Combats, where the Glory and Proſperity of their Emperor were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152938:20"/> But, the moſt part dying in theſe Occaſions, and leaving their Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences for others; it was thence eaſy for thoſe who remain'd ſucceſſively one after another, to leave the Firſt Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of their Soveraign, to paſs on continually by new Victories to new and greater Recompences: And, hence it may be believ'd, that this Abſolute Power of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s, of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Eſtates and Lives of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as he pleaſes, has taken its Riſe.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of their Religion, who receiv'd their Eſtabliſhment from the ſame Power, have not been wanting to contribute to his Greatneſs and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; teaching, That an entire Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould be paid him, ſeeing it came from <hi>God,</hi> for the Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>true Faith,</hi> and this Power which they preach'd extended to themſelves; for, they were the Firſt in obeying him, flattered by the great Advantages which their Emperors beſtowed on them, who hereby engaged them to be inviolably faithful to them, and ſubmit Religion to their Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>We need not ſearch elſewhere the Cauſe of thoſe profound and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152938:20"/> Submiſſions, with which all the <hi>Turks,</hi> of either Sex, Age, and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, humble themſelves in the Preſence, and to the Orders of their Emperors. They conſider him as the Vicar and Lieutenant of <hi>God</hi> on Earth. They render him, after <hi>God</hi> and after <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> all poſſible Honours. When they adore the Divine Majeſty, they fall on their Knees, and touch the Ground with their Heads, to ſignify they are as Nothing, before his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power. When they pray to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and in pronouncing his Name and Quality of <hi>Prophet,</hi> they fall on their Knees, and bow only the Head: And when they will render their Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> they ſtoop very low, and touch the Earth with one Hand, which they reach up afterwards to their Mouth to kiſs it, and then to their Head; to ſhew, That this Emperor being the greateſt Man on Earth, they are but Duſt in his Sight. They would alſo ſhew, that being not worthy to approach him, they think themſelves happy to kiſs the Hand, which has touch'd the Earth which his Imperial Grandure has trod
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152938:21"/> on: And they take care, never to fix their Eyes on thoſe of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> nor on his Countenance; becauſe, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as they ſay, Majeſty, Prudence, Valour, and Boldnefs in his Front, they deſerve not, neither ought to be ſo bold to look on him; it being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient that they are beheld by him.</p>
               <p>The Reſpect they bear him, is ſo well eſtabliſhed, that when he paſſes by, there's not the leaſt Noiſe heard, how great and numerous ſoever his Train may be, and thoſe that behold it. The <hi>Turks</hi> accompany theſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, with a punctual Obedience. They all, as well the greateſt as the ſmalleſt, do glory in being the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Slaves; the Term of which being taken in the ſtrict Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Law, as was that of the <hi>Romans,</hi> comprehends at leaſt an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power of his <hi>Highneſs</hi> over the Eſtates of his Subjects, ſuch as a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron may have over thoſe of his Slaves; which is to ſay, that a <hi>Turk</hi> can enjoy nothing which he has but at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Pleaſure. The great Embaſſador of <hi>Poland, John Guinski,</hi> being come to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the year 1677. with a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152938:21"/> Train of Six hundred Perſons, for the compleating the Treaty of <hi>Zouravuno;</hi> and the <hi>Grand Vizir, Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> treating him at Dinner in one of his Gardens on the Canal of the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> where this <hi>Poliſh</hi> Lord Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing him on the Beauty of the Place, and eſpecially on the Honour of being near one of the <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> the <hi>Vizir</hi> replied to him, <hi>Being all of us his</hi> Highneſſes <hi>Slaves, and our Eſtates belonging to him, he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vouchſafes to come and walk in the Gardens which we make ready for him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Law of Slavery is confirm'd by the proper Intereſt of particular <hi>Turks,</hi> who have <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Slaves, over which they have all Power, excepting that of putting them to Death, as not being inveſted with the Publick Authority. It's not ſo with the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> who, by his Abſolute Power, is Maſter not only of the Eſtates, but alſo of the Lives of his Subjects. And this Power, without any Reſerve or Reſtriction, having been originally eſtabliſhed by Conqueſts, as has been obſerv'd; their Religion has farther authorized it, and ſo ſolidly confirm'd it, that it has been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152938:22"/> ſcarcely ever ſeen oppoſed or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to any Purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Their Religion gives the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> the right of being his Subjects Heir when they die, and of peeling them in their Life-times, to the Excluſion and Prejudice of their Kindred and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, becauſe all are his Slaves. This Maxim ſeems ſomething hard, even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Senſe of the moſt able Lawyers of the Empire; but 'tis ſalv'd by ſome ſeeming Reaſon, in that the Succeſſions which the Emperor ſeizes on being the richeſt, ſeeing otherwiſe he would deſpiſe them; they muſt then be of thoſe who have had the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Treaſures, who have been Governors, or born other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Offices; or being accus'd of Injuſtice, afford a plauſible Pretence for the Seizure of their Eſtates.</p>
               <p>This Imperial Privilege is ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Uſe, that the Heirs of a rich <hi>Baſſa,</hi> or other principal Officer, altho they never fail to hide what they can, will not undertake to divide the Succeſſion which belongs to them, without the Permiſſion of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> who gives it entirely, or without reſerve, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152938:22"/> ſeldom. He cauſes the Imperial Seal to be ſet on their Goods, whether by an expreſs Meſſenger, or the Officers on the Place do it by their Authority; and, taking what ſeems good to him out of all their Riches, he diſtributes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſome Portion to the Children of him who is ſtript, whether alive or dead; and, he thinks he does them a great Favour, in allowing them the Honour of being call'd his Co-heirs. The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> poſſeſſes more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over this Right, which makes him Maſter and Owner of the Eſtates of his Subjects, eſpecially of the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, with ſo abſolute an Authority, that beſides the Perſons which he deprives at once of their Eſtates when he puts them to Death, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> gives from time to time to thoſe whom he lets enjoy their Eſtates, certain Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, which ſhould perſwade them, that this Enjoyment is only an Effect of his Imperial Benignity on Sufferance. He often viſits them, not ſo much to honour them, as to draw Preſents from them, which may paſs for the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reſt he leaves them; and he makes no Difficulty to explain himſelf
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152938:23"/> ſo, as has been ſeveral times known, eſpecially when having been entertain'd with a ſplendid Banquet, and a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Preſent by <hi>Cara Haſſanoglouſon, Aga</hi> of the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> in a Garden ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining to the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> he ſaid to him at departure, <hi>I leave thee thy Houſe, I do not take that, but remember that all thou poſſeſſeſt, to the very Fruits of the Garden, belong to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Highneſs</hi> has alſo often gon on <hi>Friday</hi> to ſay his Prayers at a certain <hi>Moſque,</hi> becauſe 'twas near ſome fine <hi>Seraglio;</hi> of which having advertiſed the Maſter, that he ſhould entertain him, and that he would do him the honour of viſiting his Houſe, this was only to receive a Preſent: This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct is ſo generally known, that they are not very willing to have Palaces near the Places where the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> paſſes and uſually walks. And a certain <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Uſurer, extreamly Rich, became once ſick with Fear, that the Reputation of his Riches would draw a Viſit to him from his <hi>Highneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Baſſa's</hi> or Governors of Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who return to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> after the Term of their Adminiſtration,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152938:23"/> paſs not over to other Dignities with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out well paying for them, and giving in Preſents whatever they have gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Employ they come out of. And to ſhew in what manner this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror attends theſe ſort of Spoils, we may obſerve an Hiſtory which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened on the Occaſion of one of his Gentlemen, named <hi>Oſman Aga.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He having caſt himſelf at the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Feet, to entreat him to grant him a Government; his <hi>Highneſs</hi> bad him think on what he ask'd, and that he might repent of it. But on <hi>Oſman</hi>'s Perſeverance, and moſt humble Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> that it would pleaſe him not only to grant him the Government for Three Years, but alſo to write the Order with his own Hand, which would take away all Fear from him during the Proſperity of his <hi>Highneſs</hi> he conſented to this: And, as he ſtill held the Pen in his Hand, he demanded whether any other would have the like Grace; but no body an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to this Invitation, except ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Gentlemen, who was a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado</hi> of <hi>Malta,</hi> who running away as faſt as he could, cryed out, <hi>God preſerve
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152938:24"/> me from it;</hi> which made the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> laugh exceedingly.</p>
               <p>The Preſents which the <hi>Grand Viſir</hi> makes him at <hi>Bairam</hi> or <hi>Eaſter</hi> (which is the beginning of their Year) and thoſe of the <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> and other Officers of the Empire; though they riſe very high, yet are reckoned as nothing, as being Rights of Obligation. But, there are a great many other occaſions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in muſt be continued theſe Preſents, which are a kind of Tribute, proper to conſerve the rank and credit of each of theſe Miniſters. Oftentimes the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> viſits them, on purpoſe to receive at the ſame time their perſonal Submiſſions and ready Money; and here 'twill not be impertinent to ſet forth, in what manner this Viſit is made.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grand Viſir</hi> being advertiſed that the Emperor comes to viſit him, goes out to meet him, about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Paces from the Gate of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace in the Street; where apperceiving his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> he makes three profound Reverences, bending very low; and kiſſes, and brings to his forehead, the hand with which he comes from touching the Ground. He places him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152938:24"/> after theſe reſpects, before the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Horſe, and marches thus on foot to the ſecond Court of his Houſe, and near a kind of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>block, on which his <hi>Highneſs</hi> deſcends from his Horſe.</p>
               <p>During this time, and whilſt he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to aſcend the Stairs, led under the arm by his <hi>Selictar</hi> or Sword-Bearer, and by the <hi>Capi Aga,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Port;</hi> the <hi>Viſir</hi> runs up immediately before, and enters into his Chamber, whence he goes out at the ſame time the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> appears at the Door of the <hi>Divan,</hi> which is a great Parlour. This Miniſter ſhews himſelf with his hands croſs his Stomach; he renews his three Reverences down to the Ground, in three meaſured Intervals, according to the largeneſs of the place; and at the third, he lets his Hands go, and conducts his Maſter on the <hi>Sofa,</hi> marching before him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sofa</hi> is a kind of Way or Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Foot high, which takes up ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally half or two thirds of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, covered with rich Tapiſtry du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Winter, and the Summer time with curious Mats of Ruſhes, neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152938:25"/> wrought, or ſome light, fine Stuff; and all about is ſpread a Quilt to ſit on, there being long Cuſhions laid on the ſide to the Wall, all covered with rich <hi>Perſia</hi> Stuffs, and the place of Honor is in the Corner, which regards the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Chamber.</p>
               <p>When his <hi>Imperial Highneſs</hi> is ſat, the <hi>Viſir</hi> puts himſelf into the poſture of a Courtier, out of the <hi>Sofa,</hi> ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up with his Hands croſs. When the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> by a ſign of his Head or Hand, orders him to ſit down, it's commonly on a little white Blanket, which is ſpread two foot diſtant from the <hi>Sofa;</hi> where the Miniſter ſits kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Heels, obſerving this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in great reſpect; whereas other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſit flat croſs-legged.</p>
               <p>Whether the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> dines at the <hi>Viſir</hi>'s or not, there's uſually plac'd, before he arrives, behind one of the Cuſhions on which he leans, five Purſes, which make two thouſand five hundred Crowns, and ſometimes more; and his Officers muſt take care to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them away after him. He is more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over preſented with two <hi>Bokchas</hi> or <hi>Toylets,</hi> in each of which, is contained
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152938:25"/> a Veſt of <hi>Martre Zibelin,</hi> and a Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Suit of Cloths, accompanyed with a Ponyard and Girdle, ſet out with Precious Stones, with three Horſes, two of which be richly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs'd. The Whole may be valued at twelve or fifteen thouſand Crowns.</p>
               <p>As oft as the <hi>Baſſa's</hi> and other great Men, and even private Perſons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Honour in being viſited by the Emperor; they are obliged to make conſiderable Preſents, according to their Rank, and exigency of Affairs. <hi>Huſſein Aga</hi> was much in his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s Mind, who for one while came almoſt every Week into a very fine Houſe he had on the Sea ſide. But finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tir'd with this two great Honour, by reaſon of the frequent Disburſment of his Money, which he loved as well as any of his Employ; he thought on a Trick which did him a Kindneſs, and which much pleaſed the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi> One Day when his <hi>Highneſs</hi> came to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him according to Cuſtom, he went to meet him farther than he was wont; and carrying him all the Keys of his Chambers, pray'd him to accept of them with his whole Houſe, which he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152938:26"/> made bold to offer him. His <hi>Highneſs</hi> well underſtanding the Meaning of this, told him laughing, <hi>Well, well, I know thou art a poor Fellow, and I am not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to eat thee out of Houſe and Home.</hi> Thus <hi>Huſſein Aga</hi> was exempt from parting with ready Money, but was forc'd to continue his other Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>Not only the <hi>Vizir</hi> and the <hi>Baſſa's</hi> never fail in their Reſpects, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to their Emperor; but moreover, when his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſends them an <hi>Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherif</hi> (which is, an Order under his Hand) accompanied with a Veſt of <hi>Martre,</hi> for which they are obliged to pay the Bearer by extraordinary Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities. The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> is pleaſed alſo, in another manner, to require Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents from thoſe that are about him. Commonly all the <hi>Ottoman Emperors</hi> are skilful in ſome Trade, or Handy-craft, wherein they ſpend their Time. This laſt <hi>Emperor</hi> was a great Artiſt at making horn-Tooth-pickers; and, when he intends to honour any <hi>Baſſa,</hi> or ſome other Perſon with Tokens of his Remembrance, he ſends him one theſe Tooth-pickers, or ſome Flower
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152938:26"/> out of a Garden where his <hi>Highneſs</hi> walks, which muſt be dearly paid for by conſiderable Gratifications to him that brings them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Particulars plainly confirm the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s abſolute Power over his Subjects Eſtates, which he ſiezes on if he thinks good, in their Life time, as well as after their Deaths. It's far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be obſerv'd, that all the chief Military Officers, as the <hi>Janizary Aga,</hi> the <hi>Seimen Bachi,</hi> General of the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the <hi>Boſtangi Bachi,</hi> Intendant over the Gard'ners, and the <hi>Topchi Bachi,</hi> great Maſter of the Artillery; are Heirs of thoſe Perſons who depend, and are in Office under them, when they have no Children. Whence it follows, That the Emperor may with greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Right, be his Subjects Heir, when they die without Children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are all his Slaves.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> are ſo far from diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Eſtates, that excepting cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Expences to which their Employs oblige them, they forget no Artifice to diſſemble their Riches; and therefore they make ſuppoſed Debts, to be thought poor, to be thereby exempted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152938:27"/> from the Envy of the Imperial Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>This Artifice becomes oftentimes uſeleſs, it being too Cuſtomary, and the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> not paying the Debts of thoſe, whoſe Eſtates he ſeizes on; for; ſuppoſing the Cauſe was to be brought to Juſtice, which never hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens when the Imperial Name is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted, there would not be wanting pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to baffle all Creditors, ſeeing the Effects cannot be ſufficient to the ſatisfying his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s demands.</p>
               <p>It's certain, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> when he will poſſeſs himſelf of the Eſtates of any of his Subjects, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the Richeſt, may eaſily do it, excepting what cannot be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. They are commonly very obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in conſigning them according to his Order, and it is more eaſy for him to put them to death, for they may conceal ſome of their Effects; but it's not the ſame with their Perſons, which they cannot conceal, but for a time, and whoſe diſobedience has ever been imperfectly upheld by Military Rebellions, ſo that they muſt yield at laſt.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152938:27"/>
               <p>It ſhould moreover be conſidered, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> knows when to take his time, as well as thoſe who are the carriers of his Orders, whoſe Execution is never attempted in vain. The Emperor's Will ſerves for a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient form of a Proceſs. If heretofore the <hi>Fetfa</hi> of the <hi>Mufti</hi> was taken in important occaſions, that is to ſay, his judgdment, or ſence on ſuch or ſuch a Fact, and what Puniſhment for Example, the Criminal might deſerve; this Formality is not now obſerved, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in important occaſions, in which the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Religion finds it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to join to the Authority of the Prince an appearance of Juſtice; to the end the Soldiery and People having knowledge of it, may concurr in the making his <hi>Highneſs</hi> obeyed, if need be, or at leaſt not reſiſt his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>It's then commonly on the inability of reſiſting, that the <hi>Turks</hi> yield their Heads. When a <hi>Capidgi Bachi,</hi> or the <hi>Haſſeki Aga,</hi> having pronounced to them from the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s part theſe or the like words, <hi>The moſt High Lord commands you to die;</hi> if they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152938:28"/> 
                  <hi>his Will be done;</hi> or, if anſwering nothing, they ask only time to ſay their Prayers, 'tis becauſe there's no avoiding the ſtroke, and therefore they make a Vertue in ſubmitting to Neceſſity. Perhaps then they draw ſome conſolation from what ſeveral of their Divines affirm, That the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> muſt be ſo obeyed, that if one refuſes him his Head, they fall into the crime of Infidelity and Apoſtacy from the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Religion; whereas, he is Crowned with Martyrdom, that obeys and embraces Death at the leaſt of his Sovereigns Orders.</p>
               <p>Yet there are few <hi>Vizirs, Baſſa's,</hi> or other Officers, who in virtue of this Maxim, have voluntarily yielded their Heads every time they could ſave it; but there have been ſeveral, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing themſelves, and doing what they could to avoid Death, yet have fell into the Precipice; and others who have ſaved themſelves, have been ſeen to die in the Employ, of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural death. A <hi>Vizir</hi> named <hi>Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> was killed flying tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted; he of the ſame Name that was Strangled after the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152938:28"/> would not have been engaged as he was after his Defeat, had he been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there were Orders to put him to Death. <hi>Firari Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Cair</hi> avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death by concealing himſelf under the Habit of a <hi>Dervis</hi> or <hi>Religious,</hi> and he died a natural death, being <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Bagdat. Haſſan Aga</hi> was ſtrangled in the very place where he had hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. There are ſeveral others who have taken, or would take the ſame courſe, endeavouring to avoid the Choler of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> as being ſuggeſted by their Enemies, without having recourſe to an open Rebellion. And they have alſo Lawyers who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, they ought not to yield their Heads, but on the contrary, defend themſelves to the laſt, and not render themſelves criminal before God, by ſuffering his Image to be ſo eaſily defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
               <p>Whence appears, with how little foundation we attribute to the <hi>Turks,</hi> this blind Obedience of embracing vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily death on the firſt Orders from the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> although they be perſwaded they do not deſerve it; and we have more regarded, in advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152938:29"/> this Propoſition, the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that die, than the manner in which they receive this puniſhment. It's uſually urged, that the <hi>Turks</hi> ſay they are all ready to give their Heads at the firſt ſign from their Emperor; but this ought to be conſidered as mere oſtentation, never putting this in practice, but when they cannot avoid it. In fine, though the obedience be blind and voluntary, or forced and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent, yet it produces its effect; and thus rendring the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute over the Lives and Eſtates of his Subjects, it is the firſt foundation of his Greatneſs and Power.</p>
               <p>The ſecond foundation of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Power of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> ariſes from the Aſcendant he has over the Politick and Civil Laws, of which he is ſo much Maſter, that he has no obligation to follow them. He can Interpret them, and even Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh them when he pleaſes, or make new ones, without receiving any kind of oppoſition, provided that they thwart not the Doctrine of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> which they regard as Divine, and deſcended from Heaven.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152938:29"/>
               <p>Yet there be found Reconciliations and Mitigations with the Maxims of their Religion; and when the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> engaged to do any thing by the intereſt of his Authority, ſhall be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to carry himſelf contrary to any Article of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> provided it be not a Capital point, he finds means enough to ſurmount all the difficulties. It's ſufficient he does it by the advice of the <hi>Mufti,</hi> without whom he ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily undertakes nothing in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Religion; being moreover cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, he will never fail to be favourable to him, becauſe a Succeſſor which his <hi>Highneſs</hi> might ſubſtitute to him, would ſoon repair the defect of his complacency.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Alcoran</hi> does not prohibit the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> the uſe of Churches, which they have always had, as long as they can ſubſiſt, and till they fall to ruin; but it forbids the reparations and the building of new ones. Yet a Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burnt, and the Ground redeemed, they will permit it to be rebuilt as it was; on the Principle, That the Law is not broke, ſeeing 'tis the ſame Church as before, and not a new one; that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152938:30"/>
'tis not a Reparation, but an entire Structure. This is a groſs ſubtilty, yet is Authoriz'd, becauſe the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Policy finds its Reckoning in it, in that, this is chiefly uſed in Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and to facilitate the Treaties of Peace; where the <hi>Turks</hi> acquiring ſo many Churches, which they proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute into <hi>Moſques,</hi> may well aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the peaceable poſſeſſion of them, provided they grant ſome one; as is ſeen, for example, at <hi>Galata,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that of St. <hi>Francis;</hi> the re-eſtabliſhment of which in recompence of the loſs of <hi>Candia,</hi> has been obtained by the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> on its anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Foundations, Redeemed by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Money.</p>
               <p>That of S. <hi>George</hi>'s belonging to the <hi>Capucins,</hi> has alſo been rebuilt by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Capitulations renewed in the year 1673. between <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> which confirm to the <hi>French</hi> King's Embaſſadors the Protection of biſhops, and <hi>Religious</hi> of the <hi>Latin</hi> Rite, the peaceable poſſeſſion of the Churches, and Exerciſes of Religion, eſpecially in favour of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Capucins.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152938:30"/>
               <p>There are other Examples, which prove, that the <hi>Mufti</hi> and the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> Law, do not only bound the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Authority, but moreover ſerve to deliver it from the Yoke, and Conſtraint, which it might lay on it ſelf; and which by a Principle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhe might think, ſhe could not be diſengaged from, although the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might procure notable prejudices to it. There has been ſeen one very remarkable, in the Perſon of <hi>Mahomet</hi> III. Great Grand-father of him who is now depoſed. He had ſworn, on ſome extraordinary occaſion, to put to death all the Embaſſadors, and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> which were to be found in his Empire, the Execution of which was to be begun in <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> foreſeeing the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of ſo barbarous and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litic a Cruelty, which would not have failed to draw along with it the Ruin of the Empire, and to procure to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes, an opportunity of revenging themſelves; oppoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Remonſtrances, and Entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to this Reſolution. But, ſeeing the Emperor ſtuck to his Oath, he had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152938:31"/> Recourſe to the <hi>Mufti,</hi> who found out an Expedient to ſatisfie his <hi>Highneſſes</hi> Conſcience, in putting to death all the Dogs of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> he having Sworn the Death of all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Dogs; and the Execution was done with Pomp on theſe Animals, which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> furniſh'd; and which perhaps they accompanyed with ſome Sums of Money to the <hi>Mufti,</hi> the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zir,</hi> and the Emperor himſelf.</p>
               <p>After theſe Proofs, and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which will be needleſs to relate, we need not doubt of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Power in his States, and over his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If it has been ſeen ſometimes agitated by great Diſorders, attended by the Death of ſome <hi>Sultans,</hi> 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are no Rules ſo well eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd, but are ſubject to ſome Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions: And it's ſurprizing, that the Conduct which has induced the <hi>Turks</hi> to put to Death ſeveral of their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and which deſerves no Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, has viſibly ſerved to preſerve and re-eſtabliſh the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power and Authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sultan Oſman</hi> would have deſtroyed the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> and transferred to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:152938:31"/> the Seat of the Empire, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Arabians.</hi> This was to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon <hi>Europe,</hi> and reſtore it to the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but the Death of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, hindred their receiving this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sultan Muſtapha</hi> had twice raiſed Diſturbance in the Order of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Succeſſion, having been preferred to his Nephews, <hi>Oſman</hi> and <hi>Murat,</hi> to whom it belonged to ſucceed; whence muſt have happened great and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Revolutions to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> had they taken hold of the Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but 'twas neglected. <hi>Sultan Ibrahim</hi> was reſpected a long time, as the Object of the Complacency of the <hi>Turks;</hi> for, his Miniſters and Subjects to ſhew him their punctual Obedience, became the Inſtruments of a thouſand Diſorders, to which he abandoned himſelf, only minding to ſatisfie his Senſuality and Diſlolutions. The Treaſures of the <hi>Seraglio</hi> (which are eſteemed Sacred Pledges, and which are only touched in great Extremities) were exhauſted, and the Conſumption of the Imperial Revenues was antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated by ſeven years; ſo that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152938:32"/> ſeemed to ſtand on the Precipice of its Ruin.</p>
               <p>Hence appears, That the <hi>Tarkiſh</hi> Monarchy has found its ſafety in the Death of theſe Three Emperors; the <hi>Firſt</hi> of which, tho brave and enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, yet very young, knew no Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics; ſeeing, to ſatisfie his Revenge on the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> who would not obey him in <hi>Poland,</hi> he hazarded, in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> the Imperial Seat, the loſing of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (the beſt Flower in his Crown) with the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi> The <hi>Second,</hi> was an Uſurper, to the prejudice of the true Heirs; and the <hi>Third,</hi> ſuch a Prodigal, as was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deſtroy the State.</p>
               <p>It ſeems, as if ſuch Events could not happen, without extraordinary Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and even without Rebellions againſt the Emperor. But it's obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that in the time of the greateſt Diſorders and Revolt, the Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents have not failed to ſhew their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Veneration, to the Imperial Blood they were to ſhed. They durſt not undertake it of their own Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, withheld by the Auguſt Quality of Emperor: but yet believing the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152938:32"/> thing neceſſary for the Preſervation of the State, they have diſpoſſeſs'd their Emperor; and putting the Lawful Succeſſor in his Place, they have obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him with pretences of Religion, to Pronounce and Write with his own Hand the Sentence of the others Death, who came from being diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of his Throne.</p>
               <p>In this manner <hi>Sultan Oſman</hi> had Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned his Uncle <hi>Sultan Muſtapha;</hi> which was juſt, ſeeing it did not belong to him to poſſeſs the Throne, to the prejudice of the other. The Uncle was revenged by the Death of this Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, not through any Principle of Juſtice, but becauſe he would deſtroy the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> and go and live at <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus.</hi> The ſame Uncle fell himſelf at laſt, to the Hereditary Right of his other Nephew, <hi>Sultan Murat, Oſman</hi>'s <hi>Brother.</hi> And <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. (who is now depoſed) was obliged to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn his Father, <hi>Sultan Ibrahim,</hi> to loſe his Life; the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> having been the Cauſes, and Executors of theſe Sentences, which they have at laſt Expiated themſelves by their own Blood, ſeeing the greateſt part of them
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152938:33"/> have been ſtrangled in different occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and with all neceſſary Secrecy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bajazet</hi> I. their Fourth <hi>Sultan,</hi> was beaten by <hi>Tamerlin,</hi> a Vagabond Prince, who came from far to make himſelf Maſter of this Emperor; who found Means to raiſe himſelf from this Fall, and to re-eſtabliſh his Affairs without the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> making any Advantage of it. His Son <hi>Mahomet</hi> I. was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to deſtroy his Brethren; whoſe Number, and different Dominations, although they were not Emperors, were on the Point of deſtroying the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> He ſubdued them without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any conſiderable Traverſes from the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and he paſſes among the <hi>Turks</hi> for the Reſtorer of the Empire, but for the perfecting of the Affliction of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> It was the Grandfather of <hi>Mahomet</hi> II. Surnam'd <hi>the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> the Thunderer.</p>
               <p>The Conqueſt of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by the ſame <hi>Mahomet</hi> II. was preſerv'd in its Beginning, notwithſtanding the Troubles and Civil Wars which ſhould make it be retaken by the <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> For, <hi>Bajazet</hi> II. Son of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and Second Emperor of this City, receiv'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152938:33"/> no Prejudice from the Diverſion which he might apprehend by his Brother <hi>Dgem,</hi> or <hi>Zidgim;</hi> whom Diſcontent, after the Death of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> made withdraw to <hi>Rhodes, Rome,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> VIII. for Aſſiſtance, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Throne with his Brother. This moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Monarch, was on the Point of carrying <hi>Dgem</hi> into the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and to make uſe of him to make War with <hi>Bajazet,</hi> and to repair at the ſame time the Miſeries which <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> II. came from bringing to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</hi> But by a ſad and wretched Example of the Blindneſs of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Dgem</hi> died empoiſon'd; whilſt, on the other hand, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> States began a War amongſt themſelves, and made ſuch Leagues, as hindred <hi>Charles</hi> VIII. from undertaking any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Infidels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Bajazet,</hi> though he had won the Battle of <hi>Chiourlou</hi> againſt his Son <hi>Selim,</hi> let him eſcape by Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and was afterwards forc'd to yield him the Empire in <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and, if for a Recompence this ingrateful Son made him loſe his Life, we have ſeen the <hi>Turks</hi> comforting themſelves
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152938:34"/> in all theſe Agitations, in that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have not known to draw Advantage thence. They qualify the Emperor <hi>Bajazet</hi> as a Martyr; they acknowledge him to be a great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror and Saint, making <hi>Elogium's</hi> of his Piety. But, to denote how far their Exaggeration reaches in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, they attribute to him by a kind of Superſtition, That having himſelf gathered up from his Cloths, his Feet, Hands and Face, all the Duſt and Sweat mingled together, gotten in Combats wherein he was; he preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſerv'd them, and ordered a Compoſition to be made of them, to put into his Tomb on his right Cheek, to profit by the Advice which the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran</hi> gives them, in theſe Terms, <hi>He whoſe Feet ſhall be fill'd with Duſt in the Lord's Battels, ſhall be by his Bounty and Divine Mercy exempt from the Pains of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selim, Bajazet</hi>'s eldeſt Son, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Parricide, paſſes alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> for one of the moſt holy Conquerors of this Empire; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereunto joined the Domination of <hi>Mecha, Medina, Egypt, Damaſcus,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152938:34"/> Jeruſalem,</hi> and all <hi>Syria,</hi> without the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of his Time attempting to oppoſe the Aggrandiſement of this <hi>Infidel</hi> Prince, the Father of the <hi>Great Solyman.</hi> It's known whereto this ſame Prince extended the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but to whatever Exceſs of Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure 'twas rais'd, he began to leave his Reſidence of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> fearing it ſhould prove ominous to him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting himſelf with giving this great Town the Marks of his Magnificence, by the ſtately <hi>Moſque</hi> which bears his Name, and other Edifices which he caus'd to be built; and, his Succeſſors <hi>Selim, Murat, Mahomet, Ahmet, Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, Oſman,</hi> and the laſt <hi>Murat,</hi> have been for the moſt part Priſoners, who never went out of this Capital.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Murat</hi> IV. would have left the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in great Diſorders, having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd before he died to have had his Brother <hi>Ibrahim</hi> put to Death, and this ſame <hi>Ibrahim</hi> was ſtrangl'd in Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the Judgment pronounced by his Son <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. whom the Army has now dethron'd. The Revolutions at the beginning of his Reign, which had almoſt overthrown it, are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152938:35"/> known, and ſo conſiderable, that he was forc'd to put to Death his Grandmother. It was cuſtomary in thoſe times, to change often the <hi>Chief Vizirs,</hi> which hindred them from taking any juſt Meaſures in the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes againſt the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> had an eaſy Means, not only to defend themſelves againſt <hi>thoſe Infidels,</hi> but moreover to deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>It has happened otherwiſe. The <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power raiſed it ſelf from the Danger wherein it was. It had for this, (by an Effect perhaps of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the Wrath of God on the <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) a <hi>Vizir</hi> named <hi>Mehemmet Kupruli.</hi> He was a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> by Birth, and the Son of a <hi>Papas,</hi> or <hi>Greek</hi> Prieſt, of a Village in <hi>Albany</hi> near <hi>Beigrade;</hi> and, though he ought to have been an Enemy to the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> yet he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their Protector, and the Reſtorer of their Empire. An Uncle by his Mother's ſide (who was chief of the Kitchin in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> in the time of <hi>Sultan Ahmet</hi>) was conſidered as the Object, and Inſtrument of his Fortune. He was ſent to this Officer, who made him immediately embrace the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152938:35"/> Religion, and procur'd him Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into one of the Chambers of the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> whence he came to the Office of <hi>Chief Vizir</hi> by different De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, during the Reigns of Five <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, Ahmet, Muſtapha, Oſman, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, Ibrahim,</hi> and during the Diſorders of the Beginning of the Reign of the Sixth <hi>Sultan, Mahomet.</hi> And when this latter being but Sixteen Years old, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Government of the Affairs of the Empire to him, <hi>Kupruli</hi> would not accept of it, till he had taken an Oath, That he would hearken to no Propoſition which directed againſt his Counſels, and that he would leave him in the Exerciſe of his Office du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his whole Life.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. kept his Word, <hi>Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruli</hi> has not been wanting for his part in re-eſtabliſhing the Affairs of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, in whatever ill Condition they then lay. It cannot enough be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that a Man, who knew neither to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>write nor read, the Son of a <hi>Greek</hi>-Prieſt, and come by chance from the Depths of <hi>Albania</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> there to make Advantage of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of a mean Officer, who had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152938:36"/> commanded nor ſerv'd in the Troops; who knew not the Sea, and was Poor; could raiſe himſelf to ſuch a Degree as <hi>Mehemmet Kupruli</hi> has done: For, not to mention that he quell'd the Domeſtick Enemies; he has been ſeen at the Head of Armies, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating foreign Forces, and taking from them whole Provinces.</p>
               <p>If this Miniſter has on one hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medi'd the Misfortunes of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, he has introduced other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries which are no leſs dangerous; for, he has deſtroyed moſt of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Janiſaries;</hi> taken off the chief Men in the Empire; made the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> leave his Reſidence at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> He has deſolated and depopulated whole Provinces by his Covetouſneſs. If he has corrected any Abuſes in the Revenues, he has ſet on Foot Pretences to levy, ſeveral times in one Year, the ſame Taxes, and to load the People with them to an intolerable Exceſs. And, it's very ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, that having reduc'd ſo many Countries of this Empire into ſo great Weakneſs, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to finiſh the Deſtruction, which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152938:36"/> the ill Policy of this Miniſter had ſo well begun; and, which was the more fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, on account of the Rebellions which happened during his governing: But, on the contrary, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> gave Leaſure to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Miniſtry, to chaſtiſe and bring down the Rebels, to deſtroy thoſe who aſpir'd to the Government, and to change no more the <hi>Vizirs;</hi> which ſerv'd not only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh the abſolute Authority of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> but moreover occaſioned the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to loſe afterwards <hi>Neuheuſel, Candia,</hi> and <hi>Caminiec,</hi> whoſe Conqueſt has not a little contributed to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Reputation of theſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's no leſs extraordinary, that the Revolts, which have cauſed the Ruine of ſo many Monarchies, have not to this time brought any Damage to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, although ſeveral have happened: And one may ſay, they have only ſerv'd, to ſhew the more the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reſpect and Obedience to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> (which is imprinted on the Hearts of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels themſelves) and what Effect the Imperial Authority produces, though
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152938:37"/> loos'd from the greateſt part of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Forces, and directed againſt thoſe within, which through Rebeili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have riſen up againſt it.</p>
               <p>There have been ſeveral Examples, during the Minority of this laſt <hi>Grand Seignior:</hi> One of the moſt conſiderable of which, was that of the <hi>Odgiack</hi> of the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> (which is an Aſſembly of chief Officers in Office and out of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.) <hi>Tcheleby Kiahia Bey, Cara Tchia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and <hi>Bektach Aga,</hi> were the Heads, and put the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> into Commotions according to their Capricio's, and Paſſions they had againſt the Officers in the <hi>Seraglio;</hi> againſt whom they pretended to have Reaſon to complain, eſpecially on occaſion of the Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Offices, and the ill Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Treaſury; with ſeveral other Pretences which they had to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe their Factions.</p>
               <p>Theſe Three Commanders found, amongſt the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> great Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions in their Favour, and Obedience in all things. The City of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> was ſubmitted to them, and the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> himſelf obeyed them, in ſending them the Heads of thoſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152938:37"/> his Palace, which they demanded with Arms in their Hands; aſſembling for this purpoſe in the <hi>Hippodrom</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> nam'd <hi>At-Meidam,</hi> which is the moſt ſpacious place in the Town, and neareſt the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Dignity began to ſhake; no Force upheld it; ſo that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to act purely by himſelf, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of Two Orders, contained in Two Pages of Paper, and confirm'd by one or Two Lines writ by his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>'s own Hand. By Virtue of the <hi>one,</hi> the Office of <hi>Janiſary Aga</hi> was given to <hi>Huſſein Aga,</hi> and <hi>Cara Tchia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> was deprived; and the <hi>Second</hi> put out <hi>Tcheleby</hi> from the Office of <hi>Kiahia Bey,</hi> and put in <hi>Caſſoum Aga</hi> in his Room.</p>
               <p>Theſe Two Orders of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, which in Appearance ſeem'd of little Authority, were carried by Two <hi>Capidgi</hi>'s, and read in full Aſſembly of the <hi>Odgiack.</hi> They produced an aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and ſuddam Effect; for, at the ſame Moment, all the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> ran to the Obedience of their new Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, abandoning the Heads of the Rebellion; one of which, <hi>Tcheleby
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152938:38"/> Kiahia Bay,</hi> intending to expreſs his Diſcontent, <hi>Caſſoum Aga,</hi> who came from being ſubſtituted in his Room, mildly ſaid to him; <hi>Be ſatisfied, this Office is not for Life, the Emperor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stows it on whom he pleaſes, I poſſeſs it now inſtead of you, and after me the</hi> Zagardgibachi, <hi>which is here, will be raiſed thereto.</hi> The Seditious ſeeing themſelves thus abandoned, were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to go to the Execution of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices given them, but they were all ſtrangled in their Way.</p>
               <p>The Power of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> or rather his Happineſs, has moreover appeared at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> in a manner which is no leſs conſiderable, in reſpect of the <hi>Spahi's;</hi> who revolting almoſt for the ſame Cauſes as the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> aſſembled out of the Town in Arms, being reſolved to make no ſmall Noiſe. The <hi>Vizir,</hi> who was <hi>Kupruli,</hi> was ſo greatly diſturb'd, that he knew not which way to turn himſelf; but, <hi>Solyman Aga,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> (who was ſince made <hi>Kiahia,</hi> or Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant under the <hi>Vizir,</hi> and lately poſſeſs'd the place of <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) drew him out of this Perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152938:38"/> He went into the midſt of the Rebels, attended only with Ten <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries,</hi> with a Paper in his Hand, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was nothing written; and, feigning that this Paper which was folded was a <hi>Hatcherif,</hi> he drew near to the chief of the Seditious, where he lifted up the Hand which held the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and with the other took hold of him by the Collar, in ſaying to him, <hi>The Emperor commands this;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Attempt to reſcue him, he led him to the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> who cauſed him to be put to Death. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed the Tumult, and imprinted ſuch Terror on the Minds of the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, who were then very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that they have had time ſince that, to change and put to Death the Principals amongſt them; ſo that the Reſt have not had the Boldneſs to form any Enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>There are many other Inſtances of the Vertue, which the only Name of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> has made to appear, in occaſions wherein his Authority ſeemed to be attack'd more nearly; but here's one which will ſhew in what manner the Veneration which is paid
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152938:39"/> him, is effectual in far diſtant Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haſſan Baſſa,</hi> the laſt of the Rebels which made a Noiſe out of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> formed a Rebellion, which he covered under pretence of oppoſing the Tyranny of <hi>Mehemmet Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruli;</hi> and having found means to draw to his Party Eight <hi>Baſſas,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Bey's</hi> of <hi>Anatolia,</hi> he ſaw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a ſmall time at the Head of an Army of Fourſcore thouſand men, threatning even the City of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi> He was greatly feared when he beſieged <hi>Burſa,</hi> before which raiſing nevertheleſs the ſiege, and being gone ſome diſtance for Money, <hi>Kupruli</hi> promis'd himſelf good Fortune from his Retreat; and, for the more ſpeedy Riddance of him, he diſpatched an <hi>Hatcherif</hi> containing the Sentence of his Death.</p>
               <p>He to whom it was entruſted, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Mourtaza Baſſa,</hi> did not believe he could execute it, by ſhewing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Orders of the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi> He alſo knew, That his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were not ſufficient to deſtroy this Rebellion; for which Reaſons he had
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152938:39"/> recourſe to Artifices, which probably had been ſuggeſted to him by <hi>Kupruli.</hi> He feigned himſelf to be of the Rebels Party, and pretended great zeal to ſerve him; and having invited him one day to a Collation, he roſe up at the end of it, and read the <hi>Hatcherif</hi> of the Death of <hi>Haſſan Baſſa,</hi> in the hearing of all the other <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> who were at the Banquet; who finding themſelves not comprehended in this dreadful Decree, and conſidering that one of their Aſſociates, who was the Bearer of it, forſook them, thought it their beſt Courſe to abandon the Condemned Party, whoſe Head, after he was ſtrangled, was ſent to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople;</hi> and this Revolt was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, the Soldiers disbanding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>There are who would conclude from this Example, that the Rebels in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, how far ſoever they may extend their Rebellion, do not believe themſelves diſobedient, nor criminal, but when the <hi>Hatcherif</hi> (which contains an Order, approved by the Hand of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>) is ſignified to them; becauſe, otherwiſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152938:40"/> they ſuppoſe that all things are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by the Authority of the <hi>Vizir;</hi> who ſatisfying his own particular Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, dares not communicate any thing of what paſſes to the <hi>Grand Seignior;</hi> and ſo that when his <hi>Highneſs</hi> by one or two Lines from his own Hand, confirms their Condemnation, they believe they have no further reaſon to doubt of it; and that they ſhall become unfaithful to their Religion, ſhould they heſitate to ſubmit to the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Commands. But to be ignorant of it, all the Precaution conſiſts, in hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring him, who is the Bearer, from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Camp; becauſe that by the reading of this Command in the Preſence of the Army, they are ſure not to eſcape Death.</p>
               <p>Theſe Arguings are o'erthrown by the very Inſtance on which they ſeem grounded; ſeeing 'tis apparent that <hi>Mourtaza Baſſa,</hi> uſed the greateſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty to compaſs his Deſign. He was far from trying the Execution of it at the Head of the Army. He had for to facilitate it, taken the Form of a Traytor; and, it's very likely, he was Maſter in the Place where the Feaſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152938:40"/> was made; and 'twas from theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, rather than on any Maxim of Religion, that <hi>Haſſan Baſſa</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to loſe his Life. Not but that a <hi>Hatcherif</hi> is extreamly reverenced, and produces great Effects, eſpecially amongſt the People; but when they are intended to allay Seditions, it is ſent againſt the Head of it. He that is the Bearer, manages himſelf with the greateſt Secrecy; and, truſting ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his Dexterity, than to the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal's ſubmiſſion, he executes his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der rather on the <hi>former</hi> Account, than the <hi>latter.</hi> In fine, notwithſtanding the Criminal obeys by Force, without rendring himſelf to the Reaſons of the Caſuiſts of his Law (who reſpect him as an <hi>Infidel</hi> that does not willingly part with his Head, as has been already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferved) the <hi>Fetfas</hi> of the <hi>Mufti,</hi> and the <hi>Hatcherifs</hi> of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> do always produce marvellous Effects, and have ever been the two Principal Means, to conſerve the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; ſeeing a Leaf of Paper, with five or ſix Words writ with his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s Hand, does more than confiderable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies could do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152938:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Several other Reaſons of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power, and particular Obſervations on the Laſt War, which the <hi>Turks</hi> had with the <hi>Emperor,</hi> the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, Poles,</hi> and <hi>Moſcovites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Turks</hi> pretend, that their Miniſters and Officers, cannot neglect their Duty, by confiding in the Protection, and familiar Acceſs they may have to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> by the truſting to their Merits, through the Number of their <hi>Partiſans,</hi> or Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and by the Quantity of their Riches, which are all Motives; which together, or ſeparately, have many times engaged ſeveral Miniſters of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes to neglect their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or to prefer their Paſſion to the Intereſt of their Prince. For, how rich ſoever an <hi>Aga, Baſſa,</hi> or <hi>Vizir</hi> may be; whatever Merit may be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally acknowledged in them, and how great ſoever the Number of their
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152938:41"/> Vaſſals may be; it's certain, that if they come to be guilty of a Fault, all their Advantages are of no Value; they ſave them not from Death, or at leaſt from running a great Riſque; but on the contrary, the more Powerful he becomes, the more reaſon is there for haſtning his Deſtruction, if he has not the Dexterity to manage himſelf very circumſpectly.</p>
               <p>It's to be obſerved, that whatever Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> may have with any one, no body ever takes the Liberty to make Anſwers, unleſs they be Dwarfs, Fools, or the Mutes of his <hi>Seraglio;</hi> who, under pretence of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting him, have great Liberty. The reſt (whatever Familiarity they may have with his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> who called the two <hi>Vizirs, Kupruli's, Lala,</hi> which is to ſay, <hi>Father</hi>) always keep themſelves in their Diſtance, without emancipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves, or departing, in any ſort, from the reſpectful Terms, in which they appear continually before him.</p>
               <p>If ſometimes the <hi>Grand Vizirs</hi> would effectually ſet before the <hi>Sultans,</hi> the neceſſity of putting ſome Perſon to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152938:42"/> Death, or, the placing another in a great Office, againſt the Cabals with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> whch hinder the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; they have remonſtrated it, as a thing abſolutely neceſſary to the Conſervation, or Welfare of the State. They declare, that the Emperor not doing it, they will deliver up to him the Imperial Seal, which is the Token of the Diſpoſſeſſion of their Office; and alſo offer their Heads, which they humbly entreat his <hi>Highneſs</hi> to accept of, if he will not yield to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances. And it has been ſeen in the Time of the <hi>Grand Vizir Kupruli,</hi> that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> now Reigning, would accept of neither one, nor the other; chooſing rather to conſent to the Death of a <hi>Baſſa,</hi> whom this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had Condemned, although his <hi>Highneſs</hi> had a great Kindneſs for him, and was perhaps grieved at his Loſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> before he left the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> to paſs the <hi>Danube,</hi> at the Head of the Army, and march againſt the <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> then in the Campain of <hi>Cheherim</hi> (of which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be made hereafter) ſeeing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152938:42"/> his <hi>Highneſs</hi> would have the <hi>Mouſſaip,</hi> his Favorite, to ſupply the place of <hi>Caima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam</hi> (or, Lieutenant of the <hi>Grand Vizir</hi>) delivered up the Seal to him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him rather to take off his Head, if he perſiſted in this Deſign. He Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to him, that the <hi>Mouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaip</hi> being his Enemy (as indeed he was) would not fail to forſake him, and not ſend him ſuch things as his Enterprize required, to the end the bad Succeſs, might fall on him his <hi>Chief Vizir;</hi> and for this reaſon, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, named <hi>Cara Ibrahim Baſſa,</hi> was made <hi>Caimacam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Power, cannot appear truly diminiſh'd; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that on the contrary, the better to eſtabliſh his Imperial Authority, thoſe who may be thought able to leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen it, are always ready to offer him their Heads. It's certain, that the Aſſurance which the <hi>Grand Vizirs</hi> take from the Dignity of their Office, to ſpeak to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> ſeldom proceeds farther than this Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance. They have done thus, as well for their own Advantage, as for that of his <hi>Highneſs;</hi> which has been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152938:43"/> obſervable of late Times, ſince <hi>Mehemmet Kupruli</hi> has o'erthrown the Intrigues of the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> This is all the Effect which the <hi>Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or</hi>'s familiarity may produce, and the Condeſcendance which he ſometimes uſes towards his Chief Miniſters; and, in reſpect of thoſe I now mentioned, <hi>Kupruli, Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> and the <hi>Mouſſaip Couloglou,</hi> its ſaid, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> reſpected the <hi>firſt,</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and loved the <hi>third.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> has mightily ſerved to eſtabliſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Limits of this Empire. Moſt of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and eſpecially the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, firmly believe, That the Bounds of Human Life being determined by the Power of God, its impoſſible to die, though a Man throws himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fire, if the Hour of his Deceaſe be not come. And, on the contrary, That another does in vain endeavour to preſerve himſelf from Dangers, ſeeing all the Cares, and Pre-cautions, cannot reſcue him from the End put to his Days, and that we muſt obey the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power of Fate, which has regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated both the Time, and Manner.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152938:43"/> Theſe Maxims have imprinted in the Minds and Actions of the Soldiery ſuch a Boldneſs, which without this would paſs for Raſhneſs; and therefore 'tis, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> with but a few Men, made in the Beginning ſuch conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Progreſſes.</p>
               <p>This Belief of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> was the ſame to them as a numerous Army, ſeeing it inſpired them with Courage, which does more than Multitudes of Soldiers. It's true, that this Intrepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity is much diminiſh'd, in Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what it was heretofore; but there are ſtill ſome Remains, eſpecially amongſt the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> and the <hi>Serden Guetchti,</hi> or, <hi>Forlorn Hope.</hi> Theſe, as well as the other Military People, do now uſe ſome Precautions; and there are ſeveral, who on the Reproaches made them touching their Flight, and ſmall Courage in certain Rencounters, ingenuouſly anſwer, <hi>Dgian Tateli, Life is ſweet;</hi> and alledge, they are in theſe Latter Times, <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and be worſted; as they were heretofore to vanquiſh or die. In fine, if the <hi>Turks</hi> be perſwaded (as they are for the moſt part) that we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152938:44"/> muſt die according as Fate has Decreed; yet they believe, their good or bad Actions, (touching which they hold Free-Will) will obtain the Glory of Paradiſe, or the Pains of Hell.</p>
               <p>They alſo hold for an unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maxim of the <hi>Alcoran, That he who dies in War, in the Emperor's Service, is a Martyr, and, if he returns Victorious, he is</hi> Mahomet<hi>'s Champion.</hi> To this purpoſe, they have oft in their Mouths theſe Words, <hi>If I die in Battel I am a Martyr; and if I return alive, having ſlain the Enemies, I ſhall be a Champion.</hi> This Conceit, at firſt produced great Effects; it engaged the <hi>Turks,</hi> with great ſatisfaction, to undertake all Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Expeditions, though never ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous, from the Aſſurance they had of loſing nothing; and, that in dying, they ſhould obtain the Remiſſion of all their Sins, except ill-gotten Goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> made not this Exception without Deſign, but that his Followers might behave themſelves with more Courage, in Rencounters wherein are great Dangers; as, in Naval Combats, where uſually there's no flying away, the <hi>Prophet</hi> has declared, <hi>That thoſe</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152938:44"/> Turks <hi>who ſhould die therein, all their Sins, none excepted, even that of ill-got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Goods, ſhall be forgiven.</hi> Thus, the Fortune of Temporal, and Eternal Life, being an infallible Motive to thoſe who periſh in the Wars, both by Sea and Land, or who return Victorious; it's no wonder, if the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperors, have been attended with ſuch proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Succeſſes.</p>
               <p>We may alſo ſay, the exact Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Rule, which has been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore amongſt the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Troops, and eſpecially amongſt the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> has been a conſiderable Means for the Aggrandizement of the Empire: And, the Method of Educating Young Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, choſen for the moſt part, out of thoſe that are taken Captive, (who are carefully inſtructed in <hi>Seminaries,</hi> or particular <hi>Seraglio's,</hi> each according as his <hi>Genius</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> ſeems to incline) is an excellent way of furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the State with Perſons capable for all Employs.</p>
               <p>Beſides what we have now mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which appears ſufficient to eſtabliſh a powerful Government, 'tis further
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152938:45"/> to be obſerv'd, That moſt of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Officers, have been always of Opinion, that the Enemies of the <hi>Port</hi> would eſteem themſelves happy, ſhould they let them enjoy their States without diſturbing them; and when they have done it, being always the firſt to begin the War, they ſee no deliverance, but by the loſs of ſome Place, and granting them always their Demands, believing it impoſſible for them, long to reſiſt ſo formidable a Power; and they cannot do better, than to gain time, and not to provoke them too much; to the neglecting, on this reaſon, the making Profit of thoſe great Advantages, which they have oft obtained againſt them, and to the carrying them on as far as they could.</p>
               <p>It's not likely, the preſent War ſhould have the ſame Succeſs; but this has been too oft ſeen in all others, which theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> have many times had with their Neighbours; as, in that of <hi>Candia,</hi> which the <hi>Republick</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> ſuſtained for ſo long a time, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which the <hi>Turks</hi> have in all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats been worſted; ſo that their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Forces, which were in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152938:45"/> near Three hundred Sail, were reduced to Forty Galleys, ill equipt, and ſome few Veſſels of <hi>Barbary:</hi> Yet, this War ended in the Loſs of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Kingdom, and, in ſuch a Treaty, as became far more favourable to the <hi>Turks,</hi> than they could dare to hope.</p>
               <p>The winning the Battle of <hi>Cotzim,</hi> which could procure the <hi>Poles</hi> nothing leſs than the taking of <hi>Bialogrod,</hi> the Paſſage of the <hi>Danube,</hi> and Conqueſt of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (according as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves own'd) did not yield them ſo much as the retaking of <hi>Caminiec,</hi> nor to ſecure <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krania</hi> and <hi>Podolia,</hi> which they have ſince yielded by the Treaty of <hi>Zourawno.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Moſcovites</hi> had (according to their General <hi>Kamadanowski</hi>'s Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) innumerable and terrible Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Souldiers, when the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> denounced War againſt them in the Year 1677. on the Difference which was between his <hi>Highneſs</hi> and the <hi>Moſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> touching the Protection given to Prince <hi>Dorozensko,</hi> and the <hi>Coſſacks.</hi> They had brought into inevitable Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the <hi>Great Vizir, Cara Muſtapha,</hi> and all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, near the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſthenes;</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:152938:46"/> where, according to the Confeſſion of the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, they might have paſt this River, of which they were Maſters, cut them in pieces, or deſtroy them with Hunger: Yet, however this happened, they hindred not the taking and Ruin of the Town and Fortreſs of <hi>Cheherim</hi> by the <hi>Infidels,</hi> nor the triumphant Return of the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zir</hi> with his broken Troops, having been as Fortunate in this Rencounter, as he had ſhew'd himſelf raſh and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</p>
               <p>The Victory of the <hi>Germans</hi> in the Battle of St. <hi>Godard,</hi> was immediately followed by a Truce prejudicial to the Emperor, by the yielding of one of his beſt Places, and Articles ſtipulated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Intereſts of his Subjects; whoſe following Diſcontents have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd to his Imperial Majeſty as much Trouble, as it has drawn Submiſſions to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> from theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples part. And one may admire, in this Occaſion, the manner of moſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, which by a certain Chain of Contingencies and different Affairs, are oft found contrary to the Firſt Cauſe producing them. The Emperor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152938:46"/> made a Peace with the <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Hungarians</hi> have ſhew'd themſelves diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, and demanded a War againſt the <hi>Infidels,</hi> to recover the Country yielded to them, and to drive them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely out of <hi>Hungary.</hi> But this great Deſire, which put them on fighting the <hi>Infidels,</hi> has at laſt termin'd, in ſubmitting themſelves and Part of the Kingdom to them. Here are Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Engagements very oppoſite; and, we muſt not wonder after this, if the <hi>Turks</hi> have ſo reſolutely expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Party.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mehemmet Kupruli,</hi> the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> thought himſelf much miſtaken in this Maxim at the Battle of <hi>Raab.</hi> He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with a kind of Raillery; for, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> March, he ask'd, <hi>Who are theſe Wenches?</hi> by reaſon of the Officers Periwigs. But when he ſaw theſe People whom he deſpiſed, were not aſtoniſh'd at the dreadful Cries, thrice reiterated, of the Name of God, <hi>Allah, allah, allah,</hi> with which the <hi>Turks</hi> do alwaies, with great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuoſity, begin their Attacks; theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> imagining to draw a great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, by the Confidence which they
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152938:47"/> ſhew in God, and the Belief that the ſurpriſing Noiſe with which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his Name all together, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to diſcourage and overthrow their Enemies; when, I ſay, the <hi>Vizir</hi> heard, that far from being affrighted, theſe pretended Wenches cry'd, <hi>Come charge through them,</hi> which was followed by a ſpeedy Execution, he perceiv'd he had not to do with Enemies who were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of him, but with ſuch as were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to exterminate him by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of all the Troops that had paſs'd the River, of which thoſe who had eſcaped the Edge of the Sword, were drown'd in their Attempts of a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
               <p>He clap'd his Hand at the ſame time to his Scimitar, to oppoſe the Flight of his Souldiers, ſome of which he kill'd; and being not able to gain his Point, he fell into ſuch an exceſs of Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as to weep, and attempt the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelf. He thought there was no Remedy, and that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> whom he derided, were coming to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their Victory on his Perſon, and the reſt of his Army: But, he came to himſelf, on the Remonſtrance which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152938:47"/> was made him, <hi>That the</hi> Germans, <hi>who commanded, would be contented with the granting a Peace from the</hi> Port.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Vizir</hi> being thus reaſſured, was glad to find his Maxim true, which he began to diſtruſt, ſeeing himſelf at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd with ſuch Succeſs. The <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Reſident was diſcours'd, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army; Deputies came from the Emperor, and the Peace was concluded with the Surrender of <hi>Neuheuſel,</hi> and the Demoliſhment of the Fort <hi>Serini.</hi> To which 'tis not hard for the <hi>Germans</hi> to find a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Excuſe for being tired with the length of the War: It's no marvel, if they deſired to be deliver'd from it, on Conditions diſadvantageous, reſerving their being reveng'd to ſome fitter Opportunity, which they now do not want.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Polanders</hi> might, according to all Probabilities, not have neglected the Advantage Heaven offer'd them at the Battle of <hi>Cotzim,</hi> in the Facility of retaking <hi>Caminiec,</hi> which was preſt with Famine, and which ſeem'd an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable Sequel of this Victory. But they choſe rather to ſet to the Pillag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152938:48"/> of <hi>Moldavia,</hi> and to feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Praiſes which all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom</hi> gave them. A juſt Title, and of which they muſt have been more worthy, had they not ſtopp'd in ſo fair a Way. But, inſtead of haſtning to the infallible Conſummation of the Triumph, by purſuing the Remains which had eſcap'd from their Victory; in ſecuring Two conſiderable Provinces from the Invaſion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and in retaking <hi>Caminiec,</hi> they return'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Poland:</hi> and have been ſince ſeen to enter into an Engagement ſo void of Precautions, that they ſaw no means of getting out of it, but by a vexatious Treaty, which they were forc'd to conclude at <hi>Zourawno,</hi> with a Precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation not uſual in ſuch Occaſions, and which ſtripp'd the <hi>Poles</hi> of the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krania</hi> and <hi>Podolia.</hi> Here's an Oppoſition very much contrary to the Cuſtom they have, of vaunting their Bravery, their Intrepidity, and Irreconcilable Hatred againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> What may one not ſay on this ſo large a Subject, and on the Cauſe of ſo deplorable a Diſgrace, which has afflicted one of the moſt valorous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152938:48"/> in the World; and which is ſo intereſted to ſuſtain this great Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſhe had obtain'd in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> wherein there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtill very ſtrong Impreſſions of it?</p>
               <p>Of the Two Peaces we now menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, one was too voluntary and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty from the <hi>Germans</hi> Part, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeems to have been concluded too generouſly from the <hi>Poles</hi> Part. It was not the ſame in reſpect of that of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> which is a moſt ſolid Proof of the admirable Conduct of a moſt ancient <hi>Republick,</hi> which having always paſt in the World for a real Example of Wiſdom, by the juſt Effects of its Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, muſt have alſo continu'd the Greatneſs of her Victories, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, if the terrible Aggrandizement of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd them to unfurniſh their Places in the <hi>Levant</hi> and <hi>Iſlands,</hi> the better to aſſure the Conſervation of thoſe in the <hi>Terra firma;</hi> which has given the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Emperors an extream Facility, ſince one Century, to uſurp a great Part of them.</p>
               <p>Theſe out-Parts of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> have been defended, to the Glory and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152938:49"/> of Religion. They have ſerv'd to blunt the greateſt Effort of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power. And it's evident, we owe to the <hi>Republick</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> the weakening and diſſipation of the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Naval Armies; which being ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant, and numerous in the Beginning, are not leſſened, or (to ſpeak better) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd, but by the vigorous Reſiſtance of the Gallies, Galeaſſes, and other <hi>Venetian</hi> Veſſels. We muſt then grant, that 'tis to their Forces and Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence on the Sea, that is due this ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable an Effect to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> That the <hi>Turks</hi> have never yet reached to <hi>Rome,</hi> but are reduc'd to that Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein we ſee them.</p>
               <p>As to the laſt War, which the <hi>Turks</hi> had with the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> on account of the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> which caus'd the Siege and Ruin of the Town and Fortreſs of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herim</hi> by theſe <hi>Infidels;</hi> its certain, that the <hi>Vizir, Cara Muſtapha,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Perſon in this Expedition, loſt therein more than half of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which was about Fourſcore thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Man, and thoſe who eſcap'd were reduc'd to extream Miſery. But to comfort himſelf in this Diſgrace, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152938:49"/> to make his Peace with his Maſter, it was enough that he had extricated himſelf out of this Difficulty, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd away <hi>Cheherim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If after the Place had been taken, the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> had remained firm camped on the ſide of the <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi> which they had happily paſs'd, to the Number of above an Hundred and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty thouſand Men, whilſt the <hi>Turks</hi> were buſied in taking and burning <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herim</hi> (which, a Man may ſay, was no more than one and the ſame thing) theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> who were before them, and dared not attack them, nor retire for fear of being charg'd, muſt have certainly periſh'd by the Rigor of the Winter, the Bogs, and Want of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, by reaſon of their Diſtance from their own Country. For ſo great an Advantage, the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> needed only have ſat ſtill, profiting by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility they have of enduring Cold, to which they are accuſtomed, and in that they were in their own Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, where they wanted nothing, through the commodiouſneſs of a great River, of which they were wholly Maſters. In fine, they were fenced on
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152938:50"/> the Land ſide, by their Retrenchment, which they call <hi>Tabour,</hi> ſo formidable to the <hi>Turks.</hi> But inſtead of receiving the Fortune which preſented her ſelf to them, they forſake her, by repaſſing the <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi> and conſtrain her to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the <hi>Infidels,</hi> whom ſhe ſeem'd to be willing to forſake.</p>
               <p>Certainly theſe <hi>Mahometans</hi> muſt mightily value themſelves, ſeeing their Enemies grow impatient on the very point of Triumphing, and give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the trouble of repaſſing a great River, to avoid a glorious Victory, which might have been gain'd by ſitting ſtill. They were in ſo low a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it's ſcarce credible; and, their Policy would not have upheld them ſo long, had not the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> been ſo prejudic'd (as they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been) in their Favour, and high Eſteem of the Power of theſe <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It has been to this time believ'd, that this Empire is another <hi>Peru</hi> for Men and Money; they have been all taken for Souldiers, Captains, and Generals of a Conſummate Experience. The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> and his <hi>Vizir,</hi> have the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152938:50"/> ſame Belief; for, by their Authority, they raiſe Men, lay continual Taxes, and place in Governments of Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and at the Head of Armies and particular Troops, Gardiners, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and other ſuch like People of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who never ſaw the Face of an Enemy. It's ſufficient a Man be <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> to be Generaliſſimo; and, that Souldiers know how to ſhoot, to fight, and overthrow their Enemies.</p>
               <p>To which we may add, thoſe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers who are wont oft to purchaſe an Exemption from going to War, and others who in ſo great Numbers exerciſe Trades. A man makes himſelf a Souldier on Foot or Horſeback, to live on pillaging and robbing the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Officers do the ſame, they be all Thieves by Neceſſity; for, they are peel'd from time to time. There are Thouſands of Souldiers, who having either Credit or Money, obtain their Pay, and are excuſed from all manner of Duty. And falſe Muſters are no where more practiſed, it being the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> himſelf, that his Companies ſhould not be compleat; this being ſo much Money ſav'd in his Coffers.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:152938:51"/>
               <p>It appears from theſe real Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and others, which the Sequel of this Diſcourſe will furniſh us withal; That, if the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Miſhap to judge ſo ill of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Power, which has cauſed them conſiderable Loſſes; his <hi>Highneſs</hi> himſelf has fallen into the like Fauit, in ſuch a manner, which is no leſs prejudicial to him: For, if he could heretofore vaunt of filling his Treaſuries, and raiſing as many Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as he would; he begins now to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that his ſo vaſt Domination end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Solitude and Deſarts, all the Money he may have will ſignify little, not finding any body to whom he may part with it, to any uſeful Purpoſe.</p>
               <p>A Man may be convinc'd of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, by conſidering his Conduct toward <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd from his firſt Enterpize, ſince he was raiſed to the Supreme <hi>Vizir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> I mean, from the Campaign of <hi>Cheherim,</hi> we now mentioned; I was then at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> His <hi>Highneſs</hi> did not ſet himſelf on reproaching him, that in ſo important an Occaſion as that was, he had ſo little Care and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152938:51"/> Foreſight, that inſtead of managing the Officers in exciting them by ſome Liberality, he had diſcouraged them in exacting Money from each of them, to the very loweſt, to keep them in their Poſts; whilſt on the other hand, he reduced them to Famine, making himſelf the Maſter of the Proviſions, which he ſold them at what rate he pleaſed. Perhaps this Irregularity, which was ſufficient to overturn all, never came to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and ſhould he have been informed of it, 'twas ſufficient there was no ill Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and the Profit the <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> had drawn hence, would have ſerv'd him as a Means, to preſs him the more to deliver into the Imperial Treaſury the Tribute he ow'd, by putting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a conſiderable Summ of the Remains of the Expence of the Campaign, after the Pay of the <hi>Militia</hi> was acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Highneſs</hi> pretended, that the <hi>Vizir</hi> ought to do it, according to the Example of the other <hi>Vizir's,</hi> his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors; it not being poſſible, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Expreſſion, that ſuch extraordinary Summs of Money, as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152938:52"/> thoſe which were raiſed, could be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely conſum'd; altho this Chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, repreſented they were, and that he would give a good Account of them. In the mean time, the Souldiers Pay was deferr'd; but his <hi>Highneſs</hi> intending not to let it be taken out of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, and his Miniſter conſtantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, he could not acquit it; the Expedient was, That the Treaſurer ſhould furniſh the Summs required, and the <hi>Vizir</hi> and Superintendant of the Exchequer, ſhould be bound to make them good.</p>
               <p>A Man may eaſily judge of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of theſe Examples, and how a War well ordered is capable of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing theſe <hi>Infidels;</hi> ſeeing, that beſides the Ruin, which may be cauſed by the reſpective Armies, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of the Maſter and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, may produce a Deſolation more effective than that of Arms.</p>
               <p>It's alſo further to be obſerved, in favour of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power, that the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeldom travel, and go not into ſtrange Countries, unleſs they be Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks, and belong to ſome Envoy, or on ſome other extraordinary Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152938:52"/> That moſt of thoſe Perſons, as well as thoſe who are in the Service of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> or <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> and in the Troops, are Men choſen for their Size and Shapes, being taken out of the Children of Tribute, or Slaves which are bought and pick'd according to Fancy. This has given Occaſion to believe, eſpecially when no other <hi>Turks</hi> have been ſeen than thoſe I now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that all in general are of this kind; whereas it's certain, that in <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky</hi> there are Perſons of ſmall Stature, and as ill Shap'd as elſewhere; they have only more Oſtentation and Vanity, and are, as much as poſſible, fill'd with their own Conceits. And I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that the <hi>Turks</hi> in general eſteem themſelves very Rich with a mean E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as they believe themſelves very knowing with a ſmall ſtock of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>It has alſo been of ſingular Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to this Empire, that moſt of thoſe who have travelled thither, have out of a vain fooliſh Humour, diſguiſed, in Favour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Truths, of which they pretend to be the faithful Relaters. This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152938:53"/> is exceeding unjuſt; the Truth ought to be made publick, that People may not be prepoſſeſs'd with theſe falſe Notions.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, if ſome do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Things clearly according to what they are, how many are there of thoſe who have travel'd thither, and even liv'd long in <hi>Turky,</hi> who have only minded their Employs, their Pleaſure or Profit, and are at their Departure leſs informed of Particulars which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the eſſential Part of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, than of Divertiſements, which are taken very diſagreeably? Inſtead of a Deſcription in general of what every one may ſay in <hi>Geography;</hi> inſtead of Relations of the Beauty or Uglineſs of the <hi>Levantine</hi> Women; inſtead of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the World with the Terror of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Arms; inſtead of writing Letters, which have made Impreſſions on Peoples Minds, by repreſenting their Abode in <hi>Turky</hi> as in a Paradiſe, and the <hi>Turks</hi> as extraordinary People; they ſhould have inſtructed the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick with what is neceſſary, for an exact Information of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and of the Hatred and Oppreſſion
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152938:53"/> of theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of the Defects of their Government and their great Weakneſs, of which it's time we ſhew the principal Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:152938:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. Of the principal Cauſes of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power, with a Deſcription of the Paſſage of the <hi>Dardanels,</hi> and a Relation of the Facility the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes have at preſent, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Firſt Cauſe of the Ruin of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, comes from the Largeſſes and Magnificences, which <hi>Sultan Solyman</hi> I. exerciſed during his Reign. He did it with ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, that having exhauſted all the Treaſures of the Empire, his Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants were conſtrained to engage their Domains, eſpecially <hi>Sultan Ibrahim,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom the Revenues were found alienated for ſeveral Years. This ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged the <hi>Grand Vizir Mehemmet Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruli</hi> (of whom we have ſpoke) to impoſe new Taxes, which were very hard; not ſo much by reaſon of the conſiderable Summs, as from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of thoſe who receiv'd them, in extorting much more than was their
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152938:54"/> Due, and requiring them to make De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations that they had paid no more than they ought. This Diſorder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the Number of <hi>Aga's</hi> or Officers, whom the Chief <hi>Vizir</hi> and, <hi>Tefterdar,</hi> ſend for the Service of the <hi>Port,</hi> and for the Exaction of theſe Rights, which ſerve for a Pretence of taking whatever they can lay hands on, and to enrich themſelves, without Fear of any Puniſhment; becauſe the Superior Miniſters ſacrificing the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Intereſt to their <hi>Particular,</hi> do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ordinarily ſatisfy their Officers, and only give them theſe ſort of Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by way of Recompence, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity of Charges, which they are forc'd to make by their Attendance.</p>
               <p>Money being the Prop and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of all States, when it flows free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Subjects to the Prince, and from the Prince to the Subjects, as well as by the good Order of Moneys, and Purity of its Kinds; one may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in this Reſpect, that the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire is fallen, and falls every Day into a great Diſorder. The Summs which have once enter'd into the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Coffers, never come out thence,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152938:55"/> but on Account of an extraordinary War, or the Structure of ſome <hi>Moſque;</hi> far from being employ'd in continual Gratifications, and innumerable Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and glorious and ſurpriſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, which maintain and enrich ſo many Thouſands of poor People, as there are ſeen authentick Examples of this in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> And, the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Money of <hi>Turky,</hi> is almoſt all falſe, or extreamly debaſed. They ſuffer great Quantities to come from ſtrange Countries, and permit it to be here currant; and thoſe who bring this Money, change it for better, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the <hi>Piaſters Sevillanes,</hi> or elſe they lay it out in Merchandiſe: Thus they carry away whatever is good in the Empire, leaving nothing but Braſs, which would have been to this preſent a real Means of inſenſibly exhauſting the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire of all its good Silver or Gold, had it not been for the great Avidity of Gain of ſome of thoſe who carry thither theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, which have been often cry'd down; as, the <hi>Oſmani's,</hi> the <hi>Temins,</hi> or Five Peny Pieces of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to's</hi> of <hi>Poland;</hi> the Loſs of which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152938:55"/> to incredible Summs, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Reference to the Five Peny Pieces, which the Merchants pay'd here at Twelve for Five Shillings, at Twenty and Eight only in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whilſt that for Five Shillings, they had Thirty, Thirty ſix, and to Forty; ſo much were they chang'd. This Money was made in the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> under the Coin of the Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Dombes;</hi> and, had the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants been contented with the Gain of <hi>Cent. pro Cent.</hi> they might have paſt as much as they would: But, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration becoming too exceſſive, which well proves the Sottiſhneſs of the <hi>Turks;</hi> they at laſt opened their Eyes, and cryed down this Money, which caus'd the Ruin of a World of People.</p>
               <p>It's not to be imagined what Fines are tolerated in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire. All thoſe who are Juſtices, do ſearch for occaſions of ſeizing on other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Eſtates; and, when there is no Murther, or Robbery committed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Extent of their Juriſdiction, (which are commonly the Two Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Means to excite them) they know how to ſuppoſe them. They cauſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152938:56"/> Blood to be ſpilt in a Quarter; they have Thieves at their devotion, or elſe they make the Door of ſome Shop to be broke open, and they require for the Blood Forty thouſand <hi>Aſpers;</hi> which they force thoſe of that Preeinct to pay, in giving the moſt apparent Strokes on the Soals of their Feet, or throwing them into Priſon. They do the ſame in reſpect of Robbery, obliging them to produce the Thief, which is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſeeing he is the Judges Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; or elſe condemning them to great Fines, which not being determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the price of Blood, theſe poor people cannot get quit, but by deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up all they are worth.</p>
               <p>Falſe Witneſſes, which are very common in the Empire, cauſe therein much Diſorder; there are for all ſorts of Affairs, and at all Prizes. They have their Agents or Curſiters, who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt at Pleadings, and fail not of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Evidences to thoſe who have been remitted to make proof by this way; and, according to the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the Affair, they furniſh more or leſs conſiderable, whoſe apparent Virtue may give Weight to the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:152938:56"/>
               <p>Fires have oft ruined, and do ruin every day ſeveral Perſons; they often happen by the Wickedneſs of certain People, who fire Houſes on purpoſe, to make advantage of the Diſorder caus'd thereby; for, they being only of Wood, and full of Painting, and beſmeared with Oily Stuff, after their manner; there are many burnt in a ſmall time. The Rapidity of this Element is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo violent, that the Inhabitants can only ſave themſelves; and a Man that is rich, and at his Eaſe, is, in the ſpace of two hours time, reduced to a ſtate of Beggary. Not only in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> but alſo in ſeveral other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there are Teſtimonies of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; and they look upon it as nothing, if there are not above four or five hundred Houſes burnt at a time. It's not long ſince the Town of <hi>Galata</hi> was wholly burnt down in the ſpace of two days; in the year following, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> received alſo the ſame Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, there being only one of the Ends of the Town which could be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Fire; and, of more than forty Fires which I ſaw, during ſeven Years continual Reſidence in this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152938:57"/> of the Empire, there have been five or fix Fires, which have conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Fifteen, Sixteen, and Twenty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Houſes.</p>
               <p>The Cauſe of the loſs of ſeveral Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, and which has deſtroyed that of the <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Greeks</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> I mean, Luxury; is now in Exceſs amongſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> They be not like thoſe Ancient <hi>Turcomans,</hi> who lay in the Fields, who never ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eat but when neceſſitated, who flept on the bare Ground, who drank only Water, and cloathed themſelves with Beaſts Skins. Theſe, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, are very commodious and rich in their Houſes, eat delicious Meats, drink Liquors mixt with Amber and Musk, and very often Wine and ſtrong Waters. The <hi>Grand Vizir, Ahmet Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruli,</hi> was ſo accuſtomed to it, that he could not meet with Drinks ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; which ſet him on making Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Eſſences, and moſt violent Liquors, of which he at laſt drank ſo great a Quantity, that he dyed three Days after. They ſleep on Beds of of Swans Feathers; and to promote ſleep, cauſe the Soals of their Feet, to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152938:57"/> be gently tickled by young Boys. They Cloath themſelves with the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Cloth, and Stuffs of Silver and Gold, eſpecially the Women, who are wholly covered with them. They make uſe of precious Furrs, and Silken Shifts; and when they go to the Army, carry along with them ſo many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Horſes, and ſo much Baggage, that beſides the delays which this cauſes, the great number of uſeleſs Mouths ſtarves the reſt.</p>
               <p>A moſt grievous Abuſe to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> and which falls always on his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Subjects, is, the bad Uſe, or the Cheat offered his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> in the gathering the Children of Tribute. This Uſage is not now ſo conſiderable as it was heretofore, although it ought to have been much encreas'd, ſeeing they were not wont to be taken but once in thirty Years, and now they are Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted every Tenth Year. The fault of this, beſides that the Countries continue eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day to be diſpeopled, is from hence, in that the Officers entruſted with this Commiſſion, deſigning their own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, ſell the Children very dear to their Fathers and Mothers, who furniſh
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152938:58"/> them with others, whom they buy of poor <hi>Turks,</hi> without being Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Thus is his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion deceived, who thinking to do an Action of Piety and Religion, by encreaſing the Number of the <hi>Muſſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> locks up in his <hi>Seraglio's, Turks</hi> inſtead of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> The Villages are hereby ruined; for, a Father im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhes himſelf, to ſave his Child; and only the Exacters make their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of theſe Diſorders, which beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and does not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi> It's certain, in proof of what I now ſay, that the <hi>Seraglio</hi> which ſtands above the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards of <hi>Perce,</hi> named <hi>Galata</hi> of <hi>Sarai,</hi> (which was one of the moſt conſiderable Places for Education of theſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, of which there were great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) ſerves only now for a Dog-Houſe, and the entertainment of ſome Gardiners.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> know not now the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the leaſt Battel. They content themſelves with being ſwift in ſeizing on ſome Poſts, in making a great Noiſe, and imprinting Fear, by running out of Order, and the dreadful Cries with
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152938:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> which they fall to Action; and, when they carry away any advantage, 'tis by Terror, by the little Reſiſtance they find, by the number of <hi>Renegadoes</hi> they have always with them, and by the greatneſs of their Numbers, rather than by any true Skill in matters of War, or true Bravery.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Janizaries,</hi> who were a <hi>Militia</hi> of the moſt Warlike Perſons, brought up under moſt exact Diſcipline, train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the conſtant Experience of Combats and Victories; are not now the leaſt ſhadow of what they have been: This was ſuch a dreadful, and well ordered Body of Troops, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> himſelf had not the liberty of diſpoſing of Offices, without the participation of the <hi>Janizary Aga,</hi> or Chief of the <hi>Janizaries.</hi> But, the Policy of the two <hi>Vizirs, Kupruli's,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo greatly exhauſted them, during the late Wars of <hi>Candia,</hi> and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome other Accidents which have ſince happened; that they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſo low an eſtate, that the <hi>Grand Vizir, Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> of his only Authority, did, during the Siege of <hi>Cheherim,</hi> deprive of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152938:59"/> the <hi>General</hi> of this <hi>Militia,</hi> for not entirely ſubmitting to his Humours. Peace has notably contributed to the Decay of this Empire. Here is excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, during this time, an univerſal pillaging, of which the People is the Source; where all the Thieves, in what number ſoever they be, come and ſtore themſelves, and apparently they'll take ſo much, that all will be found conſumed at laſt, which is palpably ſeen by the Deſertion of all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who forſake the Country, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into Towns. From <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> which are about Fifty Leagues diſtance, the moſt populous Place, and which ought to be the moſt commodious of the Empire, a man muſt carry along with him what he needs; Paſſengers lie in <hi>Hans,</hi> or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Places deſtined for Travellers, and excepting ſeven or eight Villages which he in the Roau, a Man ſees in all this Space not above Three or Four <hi>Hamlets</hi> on the right or left of this great Road. The beſt half of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is deſerted, by reaſon of the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries committed by the Miniſters of Juſtice and of the Sword, as well as
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152938:59"/> by thoſe of Religion, (as has been am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Remark'd, and to which I ſhall add the following Obſervations.)</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> buy their Employs very dear, not by the Price and Value of each Office, for there's no ſet Tax on that, but by the Intrigues, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents they muſt make to come thereto. And when once they be entered, they are obliged, tarrying in it but a ſhort time, to Rob and Tyrannize over the People, to reimburſe themſelves of their Expences, and to get ſome thing over, to paſs to other Dignities, where they pillage and commit their Rapines as before. By this means, there are ſeen an endleſs company of Thieves; and who taking all the Eſtates and Riches of the People, makes them paſs from the loweſt Offices to the greateſt. This is a perpetual Flux, which never deſcending, cauſes gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ruins. And this Diſorder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from this, that the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of this Empire, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king continually, either by Duty or Policy, Preſents to his Maſter, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to procure others from the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s and under-Officers, and theſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152938:60"/> from others, who are under them; and ſo of the reſt to the mean people, who are found to be a Sacrifice to the Covetouſneſs of both one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>The rapacious humour of <hi>Cara Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha Baſſa,</hi> tranſported him to that Exceſs, as cannot be expreſs'd; putting him on all kinds of Extortions and Violences, which might bring him in Money. He often ſold Licences for ſuch things as were forbidden, to have a pretence to ſeize on mens Perſons, and the Effects of poor people, who thought themſelves ſheltered from theſe Violences; which he ceaſed not to make them feel, under pretence that it was contrary to his knowledge they had granted them theſe Licences, but that his <hi>Kiahia,</hi> or Superintendant, had done it. There were ſeen ſeveral Examples of this Perfidiouſneſs, which he knew how to diſſemble to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> or diſcover them to him in ſuch a manner as ſhould excuſe him from blame, and lay the fault on others; eſpecially once, when the <hi>Boza</hi> was forbidden.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:152938:60"/>
               <p>This <hi>Boza,</hi> is a Drink made of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Corn, which inebriates after much drinking of it; and, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Prohibitions which the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> had ordered the <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> to iſſue out, there were ſtill ſome part of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> where the <hi>Turks</hi> went to regal themſelves with it. His <hi>Highneſs</hi> coming one day out of a <hi>Moſque,</hi> found a man who was dead drunk with this Liquor; which gave him to underſtand, as well from his own Obſervations, as what he was told by ſome attending on him, that his Commands were not obſerved. The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> ſpake with great heat about it to the <hi>Vizir,</hi> who excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf, ſaying, That he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant they ſold any more ſince his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s Order: And, having mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly thrown the blame on his <hi>Kiahia,</hi> he went in the ſame Moment to his Houſe, where he immediately cauſed his Head to be cut off, which he ſent to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> to prove the better to him, by this ſevere treatment of one of his own Creatures, his Zeal and Fidelity for the Execution of his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s Orders; who apear'd ſo
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152938:61"/> ſatisfi'd with this, that he gave him a great part of the deceaſed's Eſtate, which amounted to above a Million of Crowns, gathered only in Four Years time, wherein he had exerciſed this Office.</p>
               <p>It was muttered in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> was far from ſending his <hi>Kiahia</hi> to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> before he took off his Head, becauſe he would have inform'd his <hi>Highneſs</hi> of ſeveral Things concerning his Maſters Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, againſt which all the World ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. He was very careful to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to himſelf thoſe Parts of the Town where the Houſes had been burn'd, to build Shops; which he hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out to his own private Advantage, to the Prejudice of particular Perſons to whom the Houſes before belonged; and without conſidering, that beſides the Fire which came from ruining theſe poor People, they were farther more unhappy, in not having a Place to ſet up in.</p>
               <p>There happened in my time an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his Covetouſneſs; a Buſineſs as ridiculous, as it had been then little Cuſtomary. The <hi>Bey</hi> of <hi>Moldavia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152938:61"/> to ſend the uſual Tribute to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> of Money, propos'd to the <hi>Vizir,</hi> to ſend him inſtead of Money, certain Herds of Cattle, which he might eaſily diſpoſe of, and put a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Summ into his own Coffers. The Bargain was ſtruck, ſo that for ſome time after there was ſcarcely any thing ſeen in the Streets of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, Galata, Pera,</hi> and thoſe Parts, but Herds of He and She-Goats, of an extraordinary Strength and Stature, having each of the Males Four Horns Two Foot long, which put the <hi>Turks</hi> on faſtning them together, to hinder them from doing Miſchief. The <hi>Turks</hi> were conſtrain'd for Fifteen Days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to eat no other Meat, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other in the Butcheries; but the foreign Miniſters and chief of the Town, having had the Liberty to ſtore themſelves with Beef and Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton for that time, only the common People ſuffered, which was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Imprecations againſt the <hi>Vizir,</hi> to whom was wiſh'd, that the Fire which happened Three Months after, and burn'd the neighbouring Parts, might have conſumed the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152938:62"/> Palace, which he had in a fine part of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> but this happened not, by reaſon of his cauſing ſuch vaſt Numbers of Houſes to be pull'd down which ſtood near his, to which Loſs he would not contribute a Peny, ſaying, <hi>That if he had not done it, the Fire would have conſum'd them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the baſe Birth of the Officers of this State, and their Education, ſerve to keep them in an abſolute Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> it alſo ſhews them, that they have nothing, and that they muſt uſe all the Means imaginable to get Money. Their Juſtice, of which People are pleaſed to recite Examples, to blame the Lengths and Chican'ries of that which is exerciſed in the greateſt part of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> is for the moſt part, and at bottom, mere Violence; which, with the Avarice of the Military Officers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populating ſuch a great many Countries, has made of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Parts along the Chanal, a kind of Province, where ſeveral people are gathered together, and do ſtill flock; which has made, as I have elſewhere
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152938:62"/> obſerved, moſt of the other Parts aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and reduced this Empire to emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ruin.</p>
               <p>It's probable this may happen ere long, at leaſt, in the <hi>Europaean</hi> parts, if the Enemies of the <hi>Turks</hi> profiting by theſe Diſorders, and thoſe which it has fall'n into within theſe three or four years, do ſtrike home, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their blow. The City of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> which is Triangular, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion the fineſt Proſpect the Imagination can deſire; is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as the Heart, and nobleſt part of this Empire, on which depend all the reſt. It lies wholly open like an <hi>Amphitheatre,</hi> on little Mounts and Hillocks, to the Brinks of the Sea. It's true, ſhe has very neat high and double Walls, with good Towers at the face of its Triangle, on the ſide which looks to the Land, where ſhe is paſſing well ſecured: but, as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Perſon amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> told me, with whom I had a long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe; it's not ſo eaſie for the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to enter there, as by the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſides, which lie expoſed to the Sea, and in ſeveral places without the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152938:63"/> Walls, by reaſon the Water, Storms, and Time, have ruined them, and the <hi>Turks</hi> have never minded to repair them.</p>
               <p>All thereabouts, and what is at the Entrance of the Port Town of <hi>Scuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> Tower of <hi>Leander, Galata, Topana, Fondukli, Bechi, Ktache,</hi> the Point of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and above two Thirds of the Town, are of like Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If it ſhould chance that four or five good Veſſels, as this ſame <hi>Turk</hi> obſerved, ſhould come here, they would make ſad work with Bombs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Seraglio's</hi> and <hi>Moſques;</hi> and as for the reſt of the Town, your Fire-Pots, and other ſuch Inventions, would cauſe an univerſal Terror and Deſolation. To which would not a little contribute, a great number of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Slaves, and other people, who always are deſirous of theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders; and the Combuſtion would be the more eaſie, by means of the Wind which continually reigns there, and that the Houſes which are one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove another, by reaſon of the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Ground, are only of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, having ſeveral Balconies, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152938:63"/> great Tops of thin and fine Wood, dawbed over with Oil and Paintings, after their manner.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turk</hi> I now ſpoke of, who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſed with this freedom to me, was a <hi>Circaſſian Renegado,</hi> named <hi>Bekir Bey.</hi> He had been taken a Slave at the Age of ten Years, and brought up by a Captain <hi>Baſſa,</hi> who had gotten him the Preferment of commanding a Galley; but, eſcaping from a Wrack, which he ſuffered with Five or Six other Galleys, which were loſt in the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> he made a Vow never to leave the Land, by reaſon (ſaid he to me) that having conceived the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of returning if he could this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign into his own Country, to re-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, on occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an Inſpiration which he thought he had felt for that; God had ſhewed him by this Misfortune, that he was miſtaken, and that he could not die more happily than in the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Religion, ſeeing that was the beſt. How ſhould one doubt it? added he, conſidering the blindneſs and folly wherein God ſuffered the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to lie, in letting the <hi>Turks</hi> continually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152938:64"/> their Countries, and biting and devouring one another like Dogs, and not to have the ſence, not only not to defend themſelves from the <hi>true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> but to leave unattempted two ſimple Fortreſſes, meaning the <hi>Darda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels,</hi> and the ruining entirely <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople;</hi> ſeeing its ſo eaſy; it being plainly apparent, God preſerved this great Town, being the <hi>Zoar</hi> of the <hi>Faithful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I remember, that being with Mr. <hi>du Quéne,</hi> at the firſt Bombarding of <hi>Algiers,</hi> theſe <hi>Barbarians</hi> complained at their being Surpriz'd i'th' Night, and that the <hi>French</hi> did not do well to War againſt them with Infernal Fires, which fell from the Clouds, and with Pottage-Pots full of Powder and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſpeaking of the Carcaſſes and Bombs. <hi>Nò Star bono</hi> (ſaid they in the <hi>Moreſco</hi> Language) <hi>Franceſi Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nir à Ka di notte come ladri.</hi> They threw the Bombs by Night, to ſhun the Enemies Cannon, they being not then made to carry ſo far as now. If then theſe Pyrates, who are uſed to Fire and Combats, were ſo afrighted at them; and if the <hi>French</hi> reduced <hi>Algiers,</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:152938:64"/> which is undoubtedly one of the ſtrongeſt Maritim Towns in the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterranean,</hi> and the beſt defended by its Situation, by reaſon of a dangerous Road, and its numerous and great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery; what would become of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> in the Condition it now is, even of the <hi>Dardanels,</hi> and all the Towns of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, which are ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated on the Sea, of which Three Quarters of the Merchant-Inhabitants, <hi>Greeks, Armenians, Jews,</hi> or Slaves, do not know what Colour, nor even what kind of thing Power is?</p>
               <p>We have already ſaid, how the Houſes of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> are built. The great Commodiouſneſs of its <hi>Port,</hi> the Depth and Goodneſs of the Shoar, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which all forts of Veſſels may come to the very Doors; the Tower of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> which is almoſt in the midſt of the Water, and a little on the Coaſt of <hi>Aſia</hi> between <hi>Scutari,</hi> the Point of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and <hi>Topana,</hi> is more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for its Name, than any thing elſe; ſeeing it's only a kind of Dungeon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded by a piteous Wall, in which there is for all the Garriſon, only a poor Fiſherman and Three pieces of Cannon
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152938:65"/> without Stocks. The <hi>Turks</hi> call it <hi>Kizcoulaci,</hi> the <hi>Maids-Tower,</hi> which anſwers the Hiſtory of <hi>Leander</hi> and <hi>Hero,</hi> which we attribute to it.</p>
               <p>The Town of <hi>Scutari,</hi> which lies a little higher towards the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> is not much better ſtored with Artillery, there being not above Five or ſix Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which are near the Cuſtom-houſe, to ſalute the Veſſels; and theſe Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons (no more than thoſe which might be planted on the ſide of the Sea at <hi>Topana</hi>) do not deſerve the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, lying uncover'd on the Shoar. There's only the Artiſſery ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Point of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> which are about Four ſcore Pieces, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which we may reckon Forty of the beſt; which being taken from the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> may indeed paſs for very good ones; but then their ill Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation is to be conſidered, lying alſo open out of Walls, without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment, and the ſmall Experience, joined to the Poltronry of ſome ſorry Gardiners, with their great Sugar-loaf-Bonnets, who attend them, and which ſerve rather for an Ornament to the Entrance of the <hi>Port</hi> and the <hi>Seraglio,</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:152938:65"/> than any thing which ought to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the leaſt Sentiments of Careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or dread to Veſſels of War, who can fire their Cannon as faſt as their Muskets, and which inſult over For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes and beſt fenced Towns.</p>
               <p>All this is undoubtedly certain, and cannot by any one be gain-ſaid. But it may be anſwer'd what the <hi>Turks</hi> ſay, That for the Execution of an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize of this Conſequence, Ships with Mortar-Pieces cannot fall down from the Clouds, neither can they be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported over the Land: In a Word, That beſides the New Caſtles which ſtand at the Mouth of the Chanel of the <hi>Dardanello's,</hi> they muſt moreover paſs between the Two Caſtles which bear this Name, which have been judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hitherto inſurmountable, as well by reaſon of the Straitneſs of the Chanel, and Current, which is very rapid, as alſo becauſe there are in each about Thirty Pieces of Cannon of Twenty and Twenty five Foot long, and of Two and Three Foot Diameter in the Mouth, which carry Stone-bullets weighing Seven or eight hundred Pound, and which being pointed juſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152938:66"/> above the Water, traverſe the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel with marvellous Exactneſs, making Rebounds like a Shell, glancing on the Water from one Shoar to another, where they may be taken up, to ſerve again the Fortreſs on the other ſide. That no one has hitherto tried this Paſſage, unleſs the <hi>Venetian</hi> General <hi>Lazaro Mocenigo,</hi> who (victorious in the great Combat of the <hi>Dardanello's</hi> in the Year 1657, of which he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the Remains of the Naval Army of the <hi>Turks,</hi> whom he came from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feating) unfortunately periſhed in the Paſſage between theſe Caſtles; a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap which obliſhed the reſt of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to deſiſt from the Deſign which they had, of going to <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> All this may be true, yet hence cannot be inferr'd the Impoſſibility of the Paſſage.</p>
               <p>One may find, on the contrary, the Enterprize very eaſy, when the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be ſincerely conſidered; for, not to ſpeak of the New Caſtles, which are at too great Diſtance from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to do any great Execution, ſhould one paſs through the midſt of the Mouth of the Chanel, having been
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152938:66"/> built ſince the War of <hi>Candia,</hi> to guard the Roads which lie on both Sides, and to hinder the Stay or Deſcents of an Army, without thinking on the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which thoſe who have Wars with the <hi>Turks</hi> may take, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the Old Caſtles, by Storm, by applying the <hi>Petard,</hi> or in ſome other manner, ſeeing they have only a ſimple Wall without a Ditch, Towers, or Palliſado's: I had the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to obſerve them in this Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eſpecially that of <hi>Aſia,</hi> which is the leſs ſtrong, the laſt time I ſaw it in the Year 1682. when I went with the Captain of the <hi>French</hi> King's Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, to interpret the Diſcourſe he had with the Captain <hi>Baſſa,</hi> anchoring with all his Galleys above the Caſtles; where the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commander was ſent, by the Marquis <hi>du Quéne,</hi> who lay at Anchor between the Iſle of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedos</hi> and the Coaſt of <hi>Troyes,</hi> without conſidering that great Veſſels firing fiercely from both Sides, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture of a freſh Wind, may eaſily paſs theſe Caſtles, which after the firſt Diſcharge of their Cannon, can fire no more, by reaſon of the great
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152938:67"/> Flaſhes of Light, which perfectly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover thoſe that attend them, and that theſe Veſſels with their Sailing would ſurmount the Stream with more Swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than <hi>Mocenigo</hi>'s Galley had done, which had already paſs'd, and gone through all the Batteries of the Caſtles, when he was kill'd by a Sail-yard which fell on his Head; without uſing the Expedient ſo oft propoſed, of making the Ships of War paſs with Two other Veſſels, which on both Sides ſhould be cram'd with Wool or Earth, to deaden the Blow, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be ſecured from the Shot of theſe great Pieces in the Caſtles. There's no need of all theſe Preparations, now that with the marvellous Invention of Bombs, and the way of making them fly ſo far as they do, Two Galleys with Mortar-Pieces might beat down theſe Caſtles in Twelve Hours Time, the Weather being almoſt always fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable, by reaſon of the Shelter of the Capes; there being moreover in all Places very good Anchoring. This might be done with greater Facility, than <hi>Algiers</hi> was reduced, and other places far better provided with Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152938:67"/> and skilful Gunners, than all the Fortreſſes together of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe great Cannons of <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Ahydos,</hi> which we call <hi>Dardanello's,</hi> are retain'd and ſtopp'd by the hinder part, with Beams and Free-ſtones on the Ground; ſo that having no Stocks, they never ſuffer the leaſt Movement. So that to uſe them, it's only obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whether the Veſſel they would ſhoot at lies between both, or right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Mark or Place, which is known on the other Side of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, in which time they Fire ſuch or ſuch a Cannon, which carries not directly over-againſt, to avoid damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the oppoſite Caſtle, but a little ſlooping higher and lower on the Chanel, each of theſe Caſtles obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the other's Motions.</p>
               <p>There has not been heard of any Example, ſince the laſt <hi>Venetian</hi> War, of theſe Fortreſſes having fired any otherwiſe than to ſalute; excepting againſt a Bark, either of <hi>Genoa</hi> or <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> (if I be not miſtaken.)</p>
               <p>'Tis the Cuſtom for all Merchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who leave <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to ſtop at theſe Caſtles two Days to be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152938:68"/> to hinder the eſcapings of Slaves, the Non-payment of Cuſtoms, and counterband Goods. This Bark ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving here caſt Anchor, it did not go to the Bottom of the Sea; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried away by the Stream, it was judged on either Shoar that ſhe ſhifted away, although all her Sails were folded. I was told for certain; that both Caſtles fired all their Guns at her, without any effect, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hurt, ſave the ſending her a great deal of Water, caſt up by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds of the Bullets. It's true, this was towards the Evening; and the Fear which thoſe on Board conceiv'd, was ſo great, that ſome Seamen leap'd over-board, to get to Shoar by ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; dreading to be drowned with the Bark; which having at length got near the Shoar ſome Miles off, and the Maſter having ſome time before come down into the Caſtles to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Lading, this juſtified his Innocency.</p>
               <p>It's in truth very Fine, to ſee theſe Fortreſſes all in Fire, and to hear at the ſame time the dreadful Roaring of theſe Cannons, and the Echo's in all
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152938:68"/> the Chanel, which is bordered with Mounts: The Sea, which skips up, and becomes white with Froth, by reaſon of the Rebounds which theſe. Bullets make on the Water, and the prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Smoak mix'd with Fire accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying all this, forms a Spectacle very aſtoniſhing. I had the Pleaſure of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it, and telling Twenty five Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds of one Bullet, when I was juſt between theſe Caſtles with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>French</hi> Commander, in the time when the Captain <hi>Baſſa</hi> weighing Anchor to continue his Courſe to the <hi>White Sea,</hi> was ſaluted by ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges of all the Guns of theſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes. Which may be imputed to another Motive, than that of pure Civility or Duty to the Captain <hi>Baſſa,</hi> as knowing there was a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, who was Spectator; ſeeing, when the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Admiral paſſes, the Caſtles are wont to ſalute him but by a ſingle Diſcharge of their Cannon; whereas then, they made ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges, which we could not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, by reaſon of the great Noiſe and Smoak.</p>
               <p>The Enemies of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152938:69"/> may elude theſe Fortreſſes ſo much the eaſier, in that their Cannons are not pointed the length of the Chanel, which cannot be done without a new Conſtruction of the whole Fabrick of the Caſtles; and ſhould this be, it's obſervable that their Bullets go not ſo far by much, as an Iron Bullet of Twelve Pound would do, by reaſon of their extream Groſſneſs and Weight; ſeveral of them alſo are ſubject to be broke, by the ſtrength of the Powder. Thus Galleys with Mortar-Pieces, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above the Caſtles at a reaſonable Diſtance, may eaſily inſult over, and beat down theſe Fortreſſes, miſtakenly reputed ſo formidable. And, is it not known by every Body, ſince the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which have happened, that whoever ſhall be Maſter of the Sea, and without Apprehenſion of a Naval Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my on the Enemies Parts coming to diſturb him, may now by means of Eombs (which fly farther and almoſt as ſwift as the Cannon) make every Maritim Town ſubmit, however ſtrong it be?</p>
               <p>Only Four good Veſſels between <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedos, Troyes,</hi> the <hi>Janizaries Cape,</hi> and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152938:69"/> the Paſſage to the New Caſtles (where 'tis every where good Anchoring) would be ſufficient to hinder any Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel from coming out or into <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> which they might deſtroy with Famine, or by means of Rebellions. To hinder then the Execution of theſe Projects (which ſeem to be equally eaſy and neceſſary to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes) there muſt be Politick Reaſons, which God only can diſſipate, when he pleaſes; for, its impoſſible to believe, as ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pretend, that the Conſideration of interrupting Commerce, has been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the real Hinderance.</p>
               <p>Yet it ſeems, that Trade is ſuch a delicious Morſel, as makes it hard to be denyed; however, it's deplorable, that thoſe who are moſt intereſs'd to hinder the Aggrandiſment of the <hi>Turks,</hi> have under the ſpecious Pretence of Commerce, ſacrific'd the Intereſts of States, the Honour of Kings, and the Advantage and Encreaſe of <hi>true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> alſo have not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle profited the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire by driving out the <hi>Moors</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> from their Conqueſts, who have in great Numbers peopled the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152938:70"/> Countries, in ſupplying the Defect of natural <hi>Turks,</hi> and entertaining Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>Franck</hi> Nations. We may alſo affirm, that <hi>Rome</hi> (as Holy as it is) has contributed to the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of the <hi>Turks,</hi> by the <hi>Greeks</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in <hi>Italy,</hi> of which there are publick Colleges; who return Home after they have got Learning, where they are <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and Interpreters to <hi>Vizirs,</hi> and inſtruct the <hi>Turks</hi> in all Affairs, though never ſo diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous and pernicious to the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Reflections will exclude the Complaints of ſo great an Evil; for, in fine, thoſe over whom the <hi>Turks</hi> have made ſuch conſiderable Progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, being themſelves the Cauſes of them, it belongs to them to procure the neceſſary Remedy, and whatever Means they may have for this; yet it ſeem'd as if they never ought to have thought of them, without the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>God</hi> now puts into their Hands in the preſent War againſt the <hi>Infidels,</hi> and the Liberty all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> now has, by Enjoyment of Peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, to unite their Arms againſt theſe <hi>Infidels.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:152938:70"/>
               <p>And if this preſent Expedition does not procure the entire Ruin of the <hi>Turks,</hi> yet will it put their Empire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a great Diſorder, out of which they will never be able to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and the Arrogance of theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> will be confounded, eſpecially that of <hi>Vanli Effendi,</hi> Preacher in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi> This falſe Prophet preaching, in his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>'s Hearing, in the City of <hi>Caminiec,</hi> two Days after it was taken, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating him for this new Conqueſt; foretold him with great Aſſurance, the Conqueſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeeing that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome of their Prophecies, the <hi>Muſſulmen</hi> muſt take <hi>Spain,</hi> and in ſine, predominate over the <hi>Red Apple;</hi> for thus do they call the City of <hi>Rome, Kizil Alma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He enlarged himſelf much on this matter, but took care not to fall in his Diſcourſe on another Prophecy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by ſeveral of the moſt able Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt them, which ſays, <hi>They ſhall be driven from</hi> Rome, <hi>afterwards from</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>and the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; That this which had been ſubdued, and re-eſtabliſhed by</hi> Conſtantine the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152938:71"/> Great, <hi>was to he ſnatched from the</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>under the Reign of another</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine, <hi>by a</hi> Turkiſh Emperor <hi>named</hi> Mahomet; <hi>but, that the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>alſo ſhould retake it, during the Reign of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other</hi> Ottoman <hi>Emperor of the ſame Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be, that this taking of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> Propheſied by the <hi>Turks,</hi> has been accompliſhed by <hi>Mahamet</hi> II. in the ſame time he became Maſter of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> who was the Reſtorer of it, and who gave it its Name, having tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Imperial Seat from <hi>Rome,</hi> Enacted, it ſhould be called <hi>New Rome:</hi> For being deſirous to Erect it as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to equalize it to <hi>Ancient Rome,</hi> by the Magnificence of its Buildings, Number of its Inhabitants, and the rich Spoils, which he took from other Cities of his Obedience, to make up the Glory and Splendor of this; and, in conſequence of this, the <hi>Grand Seigniors</hi> at this day call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Koum Padichahi,</hi> Emperors of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is one of their fineſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles. In fine, if the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152938:71"/> loſt this Capital of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which was alſo that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, under the Reign of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Paleologus;</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Dracoſez;</hi> and if, for the Accompliſhment of the <hi>Turks</hi> Prophecy, he that took it was called <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the Emperor who was ſo lately Maſter of this famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and againſt whom the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have had ſuch wonderful ſucceſs, is alſo called <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may well be he, who according to the ſame Prophecy, ſhall reſtore it to the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> But if this Explication be not ſufficient, although it appears clear enough; may one not fancy after the manner of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> People, That the <hi>Turks</hi> being obliged to eat of the <hi>Apple</hi> of <hi>Diſcord,</hi> and to make it <hi>Red</hi> by the effuſion of their own <hi>Blood,</hi> ſhall ſee on themſelves the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Prophecy?</p>
               <p>It is very vexatious, that their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have not moreover made them experience this Juſtice, and let ſlip ſo many occaſions, making no advantage of the Rebellions, and conſiderable Commotions, which often, and almoſt in all times have ſhaken this <hi>Ottoman
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152938:72"/> Coloſſus.</hi> It has advanced in its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, leaving many Enemies behind it; paſt from <hi>Aſia</hi> into <hi>Europe,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out finiſhing the Conqueſts of the Countries, which lay on either ſide; it's Children and Brethren, became ſo many Uſurpers; the Son became the Aſſaſſin of the Father; Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren Fratricides, and the lawful Heir, which was in the greateſt Poſſeſſion, paſs'd no ſooner into one of the two Parts of the World, but he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led back into the other.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes have never drawn the leaſt advantage from their Diſorders (as has been obſerved) and thoſe of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have been always profitable to them. What ſatisfaction was it not to them, to ſee themſelves ſought to, as they have always been, and to ſee their ſignal faults, the loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Battels, and their frequent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, to be of no Value to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</hi> Their Enemies muſt not excuſe themſelves, on the innumerable Land and Sea-Forces, which their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations diſturbed with a pannic Fear, has made them attribute to theſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</hi> The weakneſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> on
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152938:72"/> the Sea, cannot be greater than 'tis now; and their Land-Forces, far leſs than believed, are ſo ill ordered, and led by ſo few Officers, moſt of them without Experience, eſpecially the Chief Commanders; that aſſuredly, how little ſoever we reflect hereon, and profit by theſe reflections, we may ſoon find Means, not only to free our ſelves from the Invaſions of this Enemy, but to retake with juſtice each for his part, in a ſhort time, what he has U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp'd ſince many Ages.</p>
               <p>Could it be comprehended, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> moſt of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, Colonels of Foot, and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Horſe, are drawn from the <hi>Ward-robe,</hi> the <hi>Gardens,</hi> or, <hi>Cuſtom-Houſes?</hi> that a Body of ſeven thouſand Horſe, has no more Officers, than another of three hundred, and that a Chamber, or Company of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Janizaries,</hi> have no more than one of an hundred and fifty? They are moſt certainly, very able to make a great Noiſe, to expreſs themſelves in their Diſcourſes and Writings, with emphatick and ſwelling Terms, big with Vanity and Oſtentation, extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152938:73"/> themſelves in Campaigns, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more numerous than they are, and in ſhewing themſelves deſperate on Breaches, the <hi>Scimitar</hi> in their Hands, themſelves half naked, bawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and roaring out like poſſeſs'd People, to imprint Terror, and to cut off mens Heads when they have firſt ſtruck them with this fooliſh Fear. But thoſe who are concerned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted, ſhould know how to deal with them, by the Examples which all the World has ſeen of St. <hi>Godard, Cochim, Cheherim,</hi> and lately of <hi>Vienna, Gran, Buda,</hi> &amp;c. and whatever has paſs'd, and ſtill paſſes in <hi>Poland,</hi> the <hi>Morea, Hungary, Dalmatia,</hi> even in the leaſt Rencounters, both by Sea and Land.</p>
               <p>Cannot <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> now undeceive her ſelf in this Subject? If we would expreſs the Force and Bravery of a Man, we compare him to a <hi>Turk, fierce as a Turk.</hi> In a word, this Name is a mere Phantaſm, to afright Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with which we take pleaſure to feed them, and educate them in this Fear.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:152938:73"/>
               <p>It's quite otherwiſe with the <hi>Turks,</hi> who begin in their very Infancy, and are exactly inſtructed to deſpiſe the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and to have only for them Sentiments of Hatred and Indignation. They never write, or ſpeak of us, (whatever Amity and Familiarity you have with them, even in ſpeaking to us in common Converſation), but by treating us with <hi>Ghiaour, Infidel.</hi> It ſeems as if this Hatred was Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to them; and it's certain, it's en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd by Education, and takes its greateſt ſtrength, from the adheſion of theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> to <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> and the great reſpect they have generally for whatever concerns their <hi>falſe Religion;</hi> whereas, there are but too many <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> who ſhew a great Indifferency for theirs.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have been diſmayed at the leaſt ſhock the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power has given them. They have conſidered the Conqueſts whereby that Empire has aggrandiſed her ſelf, as an inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mountable Bar; and all their Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation lies in ſaying, <hi>That the</hi> Turks <hi>never loſe, or part with any thing they are once poſſeſſed of.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:152938:74"/>
               <p>On theſe Principles they would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be at Peace with them, which is not a likely means to make them loſe, or return any thing. They have not profited by Peace, to inſtruct them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rightly of their Forces, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and Conduct as well within, as without their Empire; whereof thoſe who are intereſted, ſhould be fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, to excite in themſelves the Motions of a proportionable Zeal, for the deſtruction of this Enemy, to which they are obliged by the two moſt powerful Means in the World, <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty;</hi> and by the Glory of deſtroying ſo barbarous and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick a Government.</p>
               <p>We ſhould greatly endeavour, to diſcover perfectly the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Affairs, by a ſearch and penetration into their Policy; ſeeing that in the ſight and habit, which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king much of their weakneſſes, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of theſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> they are ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious in repreſenting them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves otherwiſe than they are.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> are ſo addicted to an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Filthineſs, which hinders Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, that notwithſtanding the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152938:74"/> Plurality of Women, there are few of them who have above four or five Children, excepting <hi>Sultan Murat,</hi> and ſome others, of whom there are mentioned extraordinary Stories. There's no doubt, but this reaſon join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Plague (which is almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in <hi>Turky,</hi> much or little, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Seaſons, and which ſometimes makes horrible Ravages) have been to this time capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this Empire into Deſarts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Number of Slaves, which are inceſſantly brought from the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, where the <hi>Turks</hi> have always Wars. The Truth of this appears, in that there are very few <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Men or Women, who have not been taken young from the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or that are not the Sons or Grandſons of <hi>Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadoes,</hi> or Slaves; who for the moſt part change their Religion, through Neceſſity or Ignorance, without a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of any. So neither is there any Houſe, where there is not for <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Maid-Servants</hi> ſeveral Slaves, eſpecially <hi>Ruſſians;</hi> and one needs only to read Hiſtory to know, That the <hi>Turks</hi> have ever tranſported
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152938:75"/> to the inward parts of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and eſpecially to <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> the chief Inhabitants of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Conqueſts, as faſt as they have enlarged their Frontiers; which they will no more do, if the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have but the Will to hinder them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Predeſtination</hi> has little effect, now a-days, in the Minds of the <hi>Turks;</hi> for though they believe it, they alſo give ſome ear to what they call Prudence, which conſiſts in the not expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſmall Numbers to great For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and, as I have already ſaid elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, moſt believe now themſelves to be <hi>predeſtinated</hi> to fly, and be worſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, juſt as they were before to vanquiſh or be ſlain. They are only ſeen not to withdraw from the Plague, which ſweeps away every year incredible Numbers of them. And, if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear obſtinate and reſolute in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining a Siege to the laſt Extremity, or, in any other occaſion; this is leſs by an effect of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> or true Bravery (although it is certain, there are people of great Courage amongſt them) than out of Deſpair, to which
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152938:75"/> they are forced, by the well grounded fear of periſhing more ignominiouſly, if they have bad Succeſs. They come to this extremity, becauſe ordinarily the greateſt Officers amongſt them ſeldom miſs of being put to Death, even when they are not in Fault; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they uſe precautions to avoid it, by keeping themſelves from Court, or withdrawing wholly from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as hath been lately done by the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Napoli de Romania,</hi> who retired to <hi>Venice</hi> with all his Family, and ſome Commanders in other places taken in the <hi>Morea,</hi> who have deſired to be tranſported into <hi>Africa.</hi> And the <hi>Grand Vizir, Solyman Baſſa,</hi> after his ill ſucceſs in the loſs of <hi>Buda,</hi> would not return to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> by reaſon of the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the manner wherein he ſhould be received.</p>
               <p>One may infer then from all theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, That it's only the ill Conduct of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which has made the <hi>Turks</hi> ſo Powerful; it being that which made the <hi>Venetian Fleet</hi> miſcarry, which conſiſted of Fourſcore and fifteen Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, ſeven Galeaſſes, and fifty Veſſels,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152938:76"/> with which they might not only have preſerved <hi>Candia,</hi> but attempted <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The extream Ignorance of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and their Contempt of whatever has not relation to their Manners, or Needs, is to them alſo a notable Prejudice. It may eaſily be diſcern'd, by what has been already ſaid; but I remember one Encounter, which for the ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Fact, I muſt relate here, as a remarkable Inſtance of their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, on occaſion of the <hi>Grand Vizir, Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> who was ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled for raiſing the Siege of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As he gave firſt Audiences (in the time he was made <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> after the death of <hi>Ahmet Kupruli</hi>) to Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, and other Miniſters of Foreign <hi>States,</hi> who paid their Viſits of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation, on account of this new Dignity; the <hi>Sieur Colier,</hi> Reſident for the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> in his Turn, made his Viſit. I happened on that day to be at the <hi>Vizir</hi>'s Houſe, where, ſeeing the Reſident enter in Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I took my place in his Train and Attendance, conſiſting of thoſe of his Nation, of whom I was known, which
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152938:76"/> commonly is far from being refuſed, it adding to the Miniſters Credit. I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted at this Audience, becauſe <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> the Embaſſador had privately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it, to avoid all ſuſpicion, and the better to underſtand what paſs'd; this was in the time of the great Diſpute of the <hi>Sofa,</hi> which has made ſuch a great noiſe. I underſtood all that the <hi>Vizir</hi> and Reſident ſaid on each hand. And becauſe the Interpreter of this Chief Miniſter, the famous <hi>Greek Maurocordato,</hi> knew not <hi>Dutch,</hi> the Reſident delivered himſelf in <hi>Italian,</hi> which was explained to the <hi>Vizir</hi> in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Language; which is not done with the <hi>French</hi> Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, who always ſpeak their own Tongue, and only uſe their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, unleſs on ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Occaſion.</p>
               <p>After the Complements, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed Civilities, the <hi>Vizir</hi> demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Reſident, What News he had from <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> he enquired, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King of <hi>France</hi> had reſtored to the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> what he had taken from them: The Reſident Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>His Maſters had recovered their
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152938:77"/> Loſſes; and that at laſt, his Majeſty had reſtored them</hi> Maeſtrich, <hi>a conſiderable Place, which was the only one remaining in his hands.</hi> The <hi>Vizir</hi> being well skilled in <hi>Geography,</hi> and as well inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Rights of Princes, drew immediately this Concluſion to the Reſident, with a Tone extreamly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, thinking he ſpake ſomething very conſiderable; <hi>You have now then</hi> Sicily <hi>and</hi> Meſſina? But the <hi>Reis-Effen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> of <hi>Secretary</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> who ſtood at his Elbow, having whiſpered him, <hi>That they belonged to the</hi> Spaniards; the Converſation ſtuck at the clearing up of this wonderful Diſcovery, and the Audience ended as is uſual, with <hi>Coffee, Sherbet,</hi> ſweet <hi>Waters,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's about three years ſince, That the Governour of <hi>Neuheuſel,</hi> as (learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> was in <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy,</hi> and Affairs of his time) made abſurd Reproaches to a <hi>French</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, named the <hi>Sieur Dalera,</hi> who was one of the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. After the Battel, and raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> wherein he was, His Majeſty of <hi>Poland</hi> ſent him to his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152938:77"/> Queen, to carry her the News, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been met with by a party of <hi>Turks,</hi> he was taken and carried to <hi>Neuheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> where he was kept a Priſoner of War. In expectation of his Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption (which was long firſt, by reaſon the <hi>Turks</hi> took him for the Queens Brother) the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> or Governour of the Town, oft diverted himſelf in trifling Diſcourſes with him. Seeing the Shooes he wore ſince ſeven or eight Months of Impriſonment, were much decayed, he ask'd him <hi>Whether he could not ſow and mend his Shooes:</hi> The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man having anſwer'd, <hi>It was never his Profeſſion; What an Animal art thou,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the <hi>Baſſa? What art thou good for, ſeeing thou canſt not mend thy things?</hi> And at the end of the detention of the <hi>Sieur Dalera,</hi> after his Ranſom was agreed on, which was thirty <hi>Turks,</hi> whom the King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſent in Exchange; the <hi>Baſſa</hi> told him, <hi>He was well perſwaded of the Bravery and Courage of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, but he could never have thought the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>ſo honeſt, as to give thirty</hi> Muſſulmen, <hi>the leaſt of which he valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Treaſure, for an helpleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who knew not ſo much as to ſow.</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:152938:78"/> But that which is more particular, and comes to my Subject, is, That one day the <hi>Baſſa</hi> argued ſeriouſly with the <hi>Sieur Dalera,</hi> on Affairs of his Time. He affirmed to him, that of all the Diſgraces which then hapned to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> his Maſter, and to the <hi>Muſſulmen,</hi> there was not one more ſenſible to him, than that which the <hi>French</hi> cauſed them; who not being their Enemies, yet gave paſſage to the King of <hi>Poland</hi> through <hi>France,</hi> to join the Imperial Army, and to ſuccour <hi>Vienna,</hi> without which the <hi>Vizir</hi> had certainly become Maſter of the Place.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> was made Admiral at Sea, when he never had made a Voyage, or knew any thing of that Profeſſion. And it's not to be imagined, that theſe Inſtances are rare and extraordinary; the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is full of them, as may be judged from thoſe I come from relating, and others which follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:152938:78"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. Proofs of the laſt Weakneſs of the <hi>Turks</hi> at Sea, with a Relation of the Affair at <hi>Chio.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Ottoman</hi> ſtrength being found much decayed, by what we have recited in the preceding Chapter, one may farther eaſily diſcover to what degree it's diminiſh'd by exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning its Naval Forces, which only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in ſome Galleys, which are not capable of making the leaſt Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>There are few Perſons, who have not heard ſeveral Relations of this; whence plainly appears, that theſe Galleys of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> ſerve ſcarcely for any thing elſe, eſpecially ſince the Peace of <hi>Candia,</hi> but only for the Collecting the <hi>Kharatch</hi> or Tribute from the Iſles, and Coaſts of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chipelago.</hi> Yet are they deſtined to clear the <hi>White Sea</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, who diſturb the Commerce of his <hi>Higneſs</hi>'s Subjects. The ſmall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152938:79"/> and Courage of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, have always appeared by the refuſal of Fighting, in avoiding the leaſt Veſſels in Rencounters, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their Galleys be all together, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by the <hi>Barbary Coſſairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was never heard, but they have been beaten, every time they have been concerned, not only with the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Army, or Galleys of <hi>Malta,</hi> but with two or three Veſſels only well uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and acting in Conſort. Inſtances are very numerous; but the World having been ſufficiently informed of all the great Fights with the <hi>Infidels,</hi> I ſhall content my ſelf with Relating only ſome particular ones, under the Officers of greateſt Reputation, who have commanded in Chief their Naval Army, and which will make it eaſily judged what the reſt are capable of doing. And we may premiſe, that whatever Advantage they may have obtained, it has been always by Chance, through Surprize; and without deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the leaſt Praiſe.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Cara Muſtapha Baſſa,</hi> of whom we have ſpoke, Commanded the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Fleet, conſiſting of fifty ſix
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152938:79"/> Galleys, he was in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> at the <hi>Port</hi> of St. <hi>Georges</hi> of <hi>Skiri,</hi> when the Galley which made the Rounds, came and gave him Notice of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Veſſel that was very near. He diſpatch'd at the ſame time Twelve Galleys, the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of which were <hi>Dourack Bey, Maſſammam,</hi> and <hi>Memmi Baſſa Oglou,</hi> to take this Veſſel, which was a <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Bark, arm'd with Twenty two Pieces of Cannon, Fifty four <hi>Candiot</hi> Souldiers, and Twenty eight Sea-men, and commanded by one <hi>Barban.</hi> This was during the War of <hi>Candia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Veſſel long withſtood theſe Twelve Galleys, and having vigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept them from coming on Board, ſhe diſguſted them from continuing the Fight. The Captain <hi>Baſſa,</hi> which was not pleaſed in ſeeing this Spectacle, reſolv'd to Advance with his whole Fleet; which having done, Drums beating, and Trumpets ſounding, the Bark was boarded, and carried away by as many Galleys as could faſten themſelves to her, and was thus tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed along by this valiant <hi>Armado.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:152938:80"/>
               <p>After this glorious Expedition, this brave General ſteer'd his Courſe near Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> commonly call'd <hi>Monte Santo,</hi> in deſign of ſearching after Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liots, or ſome other ſuch Prey as this Bark; but met with Four Veſſels of <hi>Majorca,</hi> which leaving the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Caſſandria,</hi> at the Entrance of the Gulph of <hi>Salonica,</hi> ſteer'd the ſame Courſe as he. He at firſt ſhewed great Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to attack them, and effectually made ready for that Purpoſe. They ſoon drew near the Enemies; but this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, with greater Speed commanded the Retreat, which he thought abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to his Preſervation, by reaſon of ſome Volleys of Cannon, which the chief Veſſel of <hi>Majorca</hi> made him hear very near. And he judged it more expedient to go and refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at <hi>Chio,</hi> than to engage in a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Combat, likely to leſſen the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation which he came from obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by the taking of one <hi>Venetian</hi> Bark with his Fifty ſix Galleys.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Memmi Baſſa Oglou</hi> being in the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Chio</hi> with Forty Galleys, had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that in the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Cardumila</hi> of the ſame Iſle towards <hi>Tramontane,</hi> there
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152938:80"/> was a Pirate-Veſſel; he determined to take the Opportunity of the fair Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to attack him, with all his Army. This was the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of <hi>Hoquincourt</hi> under the Flagg of <hi>Malta,</hi> who being informed of the Neighborhood of his Enemies, and having unloaded a ſmall Cargo of Coffee and Linen-Cloth, which he had taken, he hoped to have ſtill time to get out to have Sea-room to receive them. He was on the Point of compaſſing his End, when the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Galleys being arrived, thoſe of <hi>Dourak Bey,</hi> and <hi>Iſſouf Baſſa</hi> ſingling from the reſt, ſtruck againſt this Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel with that Strength, as did not a little help to clear it off the <hi>Port,</hi> without which it could not have been defended without extream Danger.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Knight,</hi> vigorouſly anſwered his Enemies Diſcharge of all their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non; and, his Souldiers and Sea-men, animated by his Example, and the Preſervation of their Liberty, ſo ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeconded him, that <hi>Dourak Bey,</hi> and <hi>Iſſouf Baſſa</hi> were obliged to cut the grapling Irons, with which their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys had faſtened his Veſſel, to get themſelves Sea-room, and conſerve the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152938:81"/> Remainders of their Rowers, leaving their grapling Irons faſtned to the Stern of his Veſſel. The great Number of Shot from the other Galleys, had extreamly damaged the whole Veſſel, and eſpecially the Maſts, which made the <hi>Turks</hi> apprehend, that with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Wind which began to riſe, they would fall on their Galleys, and take them into their Ruin; wherefore they thought it fit, to get at a greater Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>This Diſtance gave Liberty to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to put their Ropes, Sails, Maſts and Veſſel into ſome Order. The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had defended themſelves from Ten a-Clock in the Morning till Two in the Afternoon, and then being clear of the Fire and Smoak, with which they were covered, and profiting by the Wind which began to blow; they purſued their Aggreſſors, ſhowring down upon them Storms of Chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot and Bullets rain'd in with that Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, that the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Galleys were ſoon diſperſed to avoid ſuch a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and did not rejoin but to gain the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Scio,</hi> where they entered with ſuch Precipitation, that they
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152938:81"/> grievouſly battered one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Captain Baſſa,</hi> who had ſuch a great Reputation for Bravery, that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> had given him the Name of <hi>Caplan</hi> (which ſignifies, a <hi>Tyger</hi>) thought to ſignalize himſelf very much by paſſing with Forty Galleys into the <hi>Port</hi> of the Iſle of <hi>Nio,</hi> to attack the Knight of <hi>Binanville,</hi> who there took in Refreſhments with Three Veſſels which he commanded; one of which being on the Stocks, and conſequently uſeleſs, the <hi>Knight</hi> turned the Sides of the Two others towards the Enemy, without having time to weigh Anchor, as being ſurprized, and fired ſo hot upon them, that the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> General with his whole Navy durſt not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him, but was forced to retire with Loſs.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Captain Baſſa,</hi> in the Year following, thought it neceſſary to join to his Forty Galleys Six <hi>Tripoly</hi> Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and took all imaginable Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to attack in one of the <hi>Ports</hi> of the Iſle of <hi>Metelin,</hi> Captain <hi>George</hi>'s <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> who was there with his Veſſel of Forty Pieces of Cannon; attended on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with an other Veſſel far leſs, of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152938:82"/> which he was the Convoy. It's true this was ſunk after Eight or nine Hours Fight, but <hi>George's Maria</hi> held out fighting Two Days, and apparently would not have yielded notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the continuance of the Calm, had not a Cannon-ſhot took him off. His Souldiers and Sea-men fought Two Hours after, with ſuch Reſolution and Courage, as was worthy of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge which they would take for the venge which they would take for the Death of their Captain, even to the charging their Cannons with Baggs of <hi>Piaſters,</hi> having no more Bullets; but, in fine, they were obliged to render on Compoſition, which (according to the uſual Cuſtom of the <hi>Turks</hi>) was not obſerved. News was immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent of this important Victory to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> who was at <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica,</hi> for which he made publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicings, which were by ſo much the more agreeable to the People, as <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orge's Maria</hi> had the Reputation of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt dangerous Enemy, which the <hi>Turks</hi> had among the <hi>Corſarys.</hi> And his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> in Recompence of ſo heroick an Exploit, confirm'd this <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> in his Office of <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of the Seas.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152938:82"/>
               <p>The Campaign following, <hi>Captain Baſſa</hi> met in the <hi>Port</hi> of the Iſle of <hi>Eginus</hi> in the Gulph of <hi>Athens,</hi> Five Pirate Veſſels which were at Anchor, and which he went in Purſuit of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inform'd of them by a <hi>Genoeſe</hi> Bark; the Maſter of which had thought, in giving this News to the <hi>Captain Baſſa,</hi> to be exempted from making him a Preſent, as is uſual, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Admiral and other <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Commanders, never fail to exact ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of all the Veſſels they meet at Sea. <hi>Captain Baſſa</hi> prepared himſelf to fight theſe <hi>Corſary's,</hi> profiting by the favourable Conjuncture of the Weather. Theſe were the Nephew of the Chevalier of <hi>Binanville, Cruvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, Daniel,</hi> and Two others; each of which Veſſels, according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Combat, was to be attack'd by Eight Galleys, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral having thus diſpoſed the Forty, of which his Navy conſiſted.</p>
               <p>He ſet forward in good Order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Enemies, and he was ſtill Two Cannon-ſhot diſtance, when <hi>Maſſammam,</hi> the moſt intelligent and couragious <hi>Bey</hi> of his Army, whether
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152938:83"/> he thought his Artillery carried far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt, or by ſome other Motive, fired on the <hi>Corſary's. Caplan</hi> obſerving this Haſt (for the Shot reached not half way) fell into a Fit of Anger, and cry'd out to <hi>Maſſammam; Hitherto I held thee for a Man, and a good Servant of the</hi> Grand Seignior, <hi>now I have loſt all Eſteem for thee, and only Shame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to thee.</hi> After this firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge (to which the Veſſels anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red only by a Salute of Muskets out of a Bravado) the <hi>Captain Baſſa</hi> being advanced with all his Calleys, began to thunder upon the <hi>Corſary's</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Seven or Eight Hours.</p>
               <p>The Veſſeſs appeared always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable and in the ſame Condition, when a ſmall freſh Wind which began to blow, joined to the approaching of the Night, made the Galleys appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a too rude Engagement, and the rather, as judging the great firing they had made was uſeleſs, not knowing they had kill'd Four Men on <hi>Cruvillier</hi>'s Veſſel. It was judged then expedient to ſuſpend the Combat, to reflect on the Approaches of the Night, and the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which might happen, if the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152938:83"/> Wind ſhould encreaſe. And theſe pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conſiderations, were followed by a ſpeedy Retreat into the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> whence the <hi>Captain Baſſa</hi> removed into that of <hi>Napoli de Romania,</hi> where hereſted Thirty ſeven Days, for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or eight Hours of fruitleſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat; and required of the Governour of the Fort, a good Summ of Money, to deliver himſelf from the Puniſhment of being drowned, to which he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd him, becauſe in ſaluting his Army, one of the Bullets had done ſome Damage to a Galley, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Two Banks with Five Slaves.</p>
               <p>It's to be obſerv'd, that if ſince this time till the Year 1683, the Wars which the <hi>Turks</hi> have had againſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> has obliged them at different Times to a great Diverſion of their Sea-Forces on the ſide of the <hi>Euxine Sea,</hi> ſending for the moſt part to the <hi>White Sea,</hi> only <hi>Serdars,</hi> or Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generals, with far leſs Galleys; ſo is it true, that moſt of the Forces of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes are diſſipated, excepting the Six Frigats of which <hi>Mr. de la Breteche</hi> was the chief Commander, which in the Courſes they have ſteer'd
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152938:84"/> under the Flagg of <hi>Portugal,</hi> have much incommoded the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, and damnified his Subjects trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>I ſaw (being in the Year 1682, with <hi>M. du Quéne</hi> in the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Milo</hi>) <hi>Captain Manetti</hi> bring in thither a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Veſſel of Eight Guns, which he had taken only with his Galliot of Twelve or fourteen Banks. In fine, it's certain, that all thoſe Galleys where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Naval Army of the <hi>Turks</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, have for theſe Twenty five Years made no other Expedition, than on ſome wretched <hi>Petache</hi> of Five or ſix Guns, which they have ſurpriz'd in a Calm, or in ſome <hi>Port,</hi> the Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many times at Land.</p>
               <p>But, to relate other Inſtances of their want of Courage and Strength, it's apparent, that even the <hi>French</hi> King's Veſſels, have been lately ſeen in the midſt of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> daring all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Forces which came in or went out of the <hi>Port,</hi> and refuſe the Salute; had they not Hoſtages given, they ſhould have the ſame again. Never, by the ſame Reaſon, do they ſalute this
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152938:84"/> Imperial City, neither in going in nor coming out, nor the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s <hi>Seraglio,</hi> which is guarded with this Artillery heretofore mentioned, and to which all ſorts of <hi>Mahometan</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Veſſels, of what Nation ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (excepting thoſe of the <hi>French</hi> King) cannot be diſpenſed from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Homage, by firing ſeveral Guns, according to what they be, to which the <hi>Seraglio</hi> or Town diſdain to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, even to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Admiral's Flagg.</p>
               <p>This obliges the other <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> (who cannot endure this Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and will not have their Veſſels ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, without being ſaluted again) not to permit their Veſſels of War which carry any Embaſſador, or ſerve for Convoys, to enter into the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> making them tarry in the Iſles of <hi>Princes,</hi> which are at Five or ſix Leagues thence, or in the Chanel of the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> a little above or below <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> which thoſe of <hi>France</hi> are reſolved never to do, no more than the ſaluting the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, and the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who have ſometimes in vain ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152938:85"/> their Diſſatisfaction, yet paſs'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Silence this Pretention, rather than to engage in the maintaining it, in the uncertainty of the Event.</p>
               <p>In the Time of <hi>Mr. Aplemont</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding a Squadron, which had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the <hi>Marquis de Nointel Olier,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> there was a Sea-man who left one of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to turn <hi>Turk.</hi> It was judged re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to demand him; but as the <hi>Turks</hi> neither could nor would ſurrender him, under pretence he had already chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Religion, the Officer who had landed to bring him back, affirmed, that this ought not to be an Hindrance to the obtaining of this Fellow; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited at the ſame time in his <hi>Highneſs</hi>'s Arſenal, and in the Preſence of above Two hundred <hi>Turks,</hi> the Lieutenant of the Admiralty to come and ſee the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration which was going to be made to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, by other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado's, in one of the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Veſſels named the <hi>Princeſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Squadron of <hi>M. Aplemont</hi> (on which were every day perform'd the Exerciſes of Religion, as well as thoſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152938:85"/> of War, and whence the Noiſe of <hi>Bells, Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> with that of the Cannons made <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and all the <hi>Boſphorus</hi> reſound) attempted to force open the Paſſage of the <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danello's,</hi> which was diſputed them; pretending to retake the <hi>Chevalier de Beaujeu,</hi> who had eſcaped out of the Seven Towers into the King's Veſſels, with Three or four other Slaves of Conſideration, belonging to <hi>Cara Muſtapha Baſſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Obſervations cauſed by divers Events in all the Campaigns of this preſent War, and by the Detention for above a Month (which Twelve <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Veſſels and Two Fire-ſhips have made in the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Rhodes</hi>) of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Naval Army, who dared not come out, though conſiſting of Forty eight Galleys and Twenty ſeven Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of War, to wit, Ten great ones newly built at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſeven <hi>Tripolines,</hi> and Ten or twelve <hi>Algerines; Tunis</hi> not being able to furniſh any, by reaſon of its own Inteſtin Troubles: All this Fleet muſt have been famiſhed, or neceſſitated to accept of Combat, had not the <hi>Venetian</hi> Veſſels left their
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152938:86"/> Poſt to join the Body of their Army, to continue the Expeditions of the <hi>Morea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We were told at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> that the Siege of <hi>Coron</hi> obliged the <hi>Turks</hi> for the ſuccouring of the Place, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade whatever they had on their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys; and the ſame Advice alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd us, that of all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, there were not above Five or ſix Galleys, which returned fit for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and, ſince that, we have heard that all this Fleet was moreover in a piteous Condition, having neither Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nor Bullets; that Diviſions and Revolts were common amongſt the Souldiers, and that they had ſcarcely and Sea-Men; that the Ten great Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> were good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, being built of green Wood, and by bad Workmen, which had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the Loſs of one of the greateſt, being ſunk without one Mans ſaving himſelf who was thereon. They alſo parted in ſuch Haſt, that there were Two of them, which could not take in their Guns, but in paſſing by the Caſtles, and at <hi>Tenedos,</hi> where the other Veſſels gave them ſome Pieces.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:152938:86"/>
               <p>The Plague and Scarcity (which have been extraordinary great this Year at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as well as amongſt the Troops) cauſes amongſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple an horrible Conſternation; and ſo much the more, that flattering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the retaking of the Places conquered by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> as well as the raiſing the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> to Flight, for which they made Bonfires; they have felt the Falſity of all this News, by their want of Corn and other Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which <hi>Greece,</hi> and the <hi>White Sea</hi> yielded this Capital City; and that the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> on the contrary, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſtill to advance by new and more important Conqueſts, and by the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of their Veſſels at Sea. They alſo write, That <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> is in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Apprehenſion, leſt the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> ſhould come by the <hi>Black Sea</hi> to ravage the Chanel, and even the Suburbs of the Town, as has been ſeen hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and its fear'd, for the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Miſeries, leſt the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſhould block up the Chanel of the <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danello's</hi> to come and fire all therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, and famiſh the Town, by ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing <hi>Tenedos,</hi> and keeping the Roads
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152938:87"/> which lie near the firſt Caſtles.</p>
               <p>In fine, ſeveral People in <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> have long ago begun to prepare themſelves to leave that City, to paſs into <hi>Aſia:</hi> The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is exhauſted, and there are great Deſertions, and Mutinies amongſt the Souldiers, who pillage and uſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants as they liſt. And who knows what Confuſions and Inſurrections this late Action of the Army (of depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Emperor, <hi>Sultan Mahomet,</hi> who had reigned Eight and forty Years, and ſetting up his Brother <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Solyman</hi> in his place) may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce? But what will they do, and what will become of them, if their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies act as powerfully as they are able; and if it be true, that Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions begin to ariſe in <hi>Egypt</hi> and other Parts? In a word, however great and formidable Armies they are ſaid to have, to defend or ſuccour a Place; could they hinder the Loſs of <hi>Buda?</hi> Has there been any general or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Battle in <hi>Hungary, Greece</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> which they have not loſt? Has there been any Veſſel ſeen to hinder the Conqueſt of <hi>Coron, Navarrin,</hi> St.
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152938:87"/> 
                  <hi>Maure, Modon, Napoli de Romania,</hi> and other Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es, where the <hi>Venetians</hi> behave themſelves ſo bravely both by Sea and Land? Where is then this great Power?</p>
               <p>Troops and whole Armies have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed preſented themſelves to hinder theſe Exploits; but has not this been rather to encreaſe the Reputation of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Arms, and the better to prove the Propoſition which we have aſſerted, <hi>of the Invalidity at preſent of the</hi> Ottoman <hi>Troops, and the extream Weakneſs of theſe</hi> Infidels? Beſides what has paſs'd in the Conqueſt of <hi>Buda,</hi> in the Preſence of a freſh Army, which was the Witneſs of it (an Action re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Worthy the Blood of ſo many Princes, who, in Imitation of their Head, have ſo valiantly ſhewed their Courage and Reſolution) one may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo remark a like ſtate of Affairs in the taking of <hi>Coron,</hi> where General <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſini,</hi> having only Eight thouſand Men when he beſieged this Place, finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf inveſted and hemm'd in by the <hi>Ser aſquier</hi> at the Head of Ten thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> who hold him beſieged, and in great likelyhood of deſtroying him
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152938:88"/> with all his Army: But, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Danger, and the Fatigues of above Thirty Days vigorous Siege; notwithſtanding the Obſtinacy of the Garriſon of the Place, and the Loſs of near Two thouſand Souldiers; <hi>Moro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſini</hi> does not only defend his Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation, but cuts on one hand all the <hi>Turks</hi> in pieces, and on the other car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries away the Town by Aſſault.</p>
               <p>What happen'd at the taking of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli de Romania,</hi> and which well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the extraordinary Rejoicings which have been made, does appear ſtill more honourable to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> ſeeing that at the end of a Campaign, after ſeveral Places already ſubdued by Sieges, and fierce Combats; we ſee theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> beaten on their own Ground, as often as they offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by an Army which comes from far, which is obliged to diſembark, and which the Sick alone have weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened to an half part: And it's on this Account, as well as on others, that the Bravery and Conduct of <hi>Moroſini,</hi> render him worthy of immortal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and of the Honours which the ſerene <hi>Republick</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> (in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152938:88"/> of the great Services done to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and to her ſelf in particular) has taken pleaſure to heap on the Perſon and Family of this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</p>
               <p>The Illuſtrious <hi>Venier</hi> had only Three Veſſels, with which he came from transporting to <hi>Tenedos</hi> the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Napoli de Romania,</hi> in purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Capitulation granted to this Place: And, having been expected at his Return by Twenty Galleys of <hi>Beigs,</hi> and Seven or eight <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Veſſels, which would have fallen on him againſt all Juſtice and Rules of War; he fought them ſo vigorouſly, that he ſunk ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of their Veſſels, and the Galleys needed much their Oars and Swiftneſs, to ſave themſelves from an entire Ruin.</p>
               <p>It's not then neceſſary, after what has been mentioned, to relate any thing elſe, to ſhew the Extremity and wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed State whereto the <hi>Turks</hi> are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in all Parts and in all Manners. Theſe are not the Armies, nor pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Fleets, which have appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Mahomet</hi> II. under the <hi>Solymans</hi> and <hi>Selims.</hi> In fine, all the World being
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152938:89"/> ſufficiently inſtructed of what actually paſſes againſt theſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> we ought no longer to inſiſt on the ſad Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which had plung'd almoſt all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> in a lethargick Benumm'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſeeing there are at preſent ſo many others, which ought to inipire contrary Sentiments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:152938:89"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. Some Politick Reflections, on the preſent ill Condition of the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Affairs, ſince the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Siege of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes were wont to think themſelves Happy, when they were not attack'd by ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Enemies as the <hi>Turks;</hi> and, if they were, 'twas alwaies thought the beſt Courſe, to endeavour a Peace, and not to do their utmoſt againſt them. We have recited ſufficient Examples, but may we not with Grief ſtill ſay, that what paſs'd laſt at <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> when the <hi>Turks</hi> invaded <hi>Hungary,</hi> and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> was an Effect of this pernicious Maxim?</p>
               <p>They diſputed at the <hi>Diet</hi> on Preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, and ſought the Security of <hi>Germany</hi> on the ſide of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> where there were no Enemies, whilſt it was preſſed on the <hi>Danube,</hi> by thoſe who were ſaid to be ſo formidable. One might infer, That they were afraid
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152938:90"/> of diſobliging the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> in only thinking of Means to oppoſe the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, which threatned <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and all <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> and if they beſieged immediately <hi>Neuheuſel,</hi> would it not ſeem that it was an Enterprize of pure Hazard, and to acquire Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (in ſhewing they were ready to act againſt theſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> who were thought as yet far diſtant) were one not otherwiſe extraordinary well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, of the Bravery, wiſe and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Conduct of Prince <hi>Charles de Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One might alſo ſay, That if the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Vienna</hi> had not been of ſo great Importance they would have given to the <hi>Turks</hi> this Conqueſt. There was an abſolute neceſſity of rowſing on this occaſion; but, no ſooner were theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> retreated, but the fear (perhaps) of irritating them too much, made them not be purſued; yet this might having eaſily been, according to all appearances; and the Victuals and Munitions, which they left in their Camp, facilitated this happy and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſequel, of the raiſing of a Siege, and of a Defeat; which without doubt
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152938:90"/> might have had from this Campaign a greater Succeſs; the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might have been better ſeconded, and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Affairs might have been a great deal forwarder than they are now. But the Ceremonials which were to be obſerved in the Town delivered, between the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the fear the Army had of the flying Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies returning, occaſioned the Loſs of ſeveral Meaſures, and much time: And this was it which produced the Safety and Preſervation of the reſt of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Troops.</p>
               <p>How could they have eſcaped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many difficult Paſſes, Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Rivers, and Mountains; ſeeing, that having had the Means of reaſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelves, yet fell they, for all this, into great Confuſion, and that Diſorder, which commonly attends an Army cut in pieces? Its certain, that the Soldiers of both Horſe and Foot, arrived at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and other Places, moſt of them quite naked, and kill'd one another for a bit of Bread; and that they pillaged, and waſted their own Maſters Country. What great
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152938:91"/> Advantages might not have been drawn from ſuch a Flight; and why did not the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> immediately take hold of it?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> believed for a great while, That the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> followed them and would ſoon be on their Backs; there were Rebellions amongſt them at this very time. But if they abandoned <hi>Vienna</hi> very briskly, it muſt alſo be granted, That the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who contributed to this good Fortune, as well by their Preſence, as force of their Arms, remained themſelves in a kind of Enchantment at ſo great a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and had not (as one may ſay) the Liberty of reflecting, That Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who fled ſo faſt, and in ſo great Diſorder, although they had ſuffered but ſmall Efforts, were not ſo redoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as they were fancy'd.</p>
               <p>They had neither, in effect, the Number of Troops, nor Conduct, nor Officers, as was imagined. But if notwithſtanding all this, the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> did not take the advantage of their Victory; ſo its certain, that if the <hi>Turks</hi> had taken <hi>Vienna,</hi> they would not have faln into the ſame fault, but
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152938:91"/> have deſolated all <hi>Germany,</hi> or ſet it under Tribute, and even <hi>Italy</hi> too.</p>
               <p>They are now far from ſo high a point of Glory, and do every day more decline; but that which ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their Conſternation and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wherein they are, is, that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do, nor can blame any but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and that it cannot be ſaid, 'tis the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to whom belongs the Honour of beginning ſo great a Work, ſeeing the firſt Circumſtance, and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin which has cauſed ſuch dreadful Effects for theſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> comes preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the <hi>Grand Vizir, Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha Baſſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was of Advantage to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> that the Ignorance, Pride, and Avarice of this Chief Miniſter (which I have ſufficiently denoted) ſhould make him loſe all rational Meaſures. It was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Fines and Perſecutions, which he was wont to offer the Miniſters of the Neighbouring <hi>States,</hi> which reſided at the <hi>Port,</hi> would be at length capable of exciting their Maſters, to reſent them at a fitting time; and, perhaps he would have been continued in theſe Exceſſes, had not his Brutiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152938:92"/> tranſported him beyond all Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>He had ſeen the Empire of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> willing to purchaſe his Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at any rate, to the Honour and Advantage of the <hi>Port.</hi> This <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Miniſter might have eaſily percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That in favouring thus the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> with his Maſters good Will, he might have had the Pleaſure of ſeeing all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> bent one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which would have yielded him an advantageous Opportunity of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking them, when he pleaſed. He might have contented himſelf, with giving directly ſome Aſſiſtance to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Malecontents, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored the Protection of the <hi>Port,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out openly declaring himſelf againſt the <hi>Germans.</hi> He might have kept himſelf quiet, and renewed the Truce with the <hi>Emperor</hi> to the Advantage of his Maſter; but, by a ſingular Grace of <hi>God,</hi> in favour of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> he paſs'd over all theſe Conſiderations; and one may ſay, that in making War with the Emperor, and putting all <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Auſtria</hi> into Confuſion, he could not have procured a greater
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152938:92"/> advantage to the Empire. He has unblinded <hi>Chriſterdom,</hi> and made her know what kind of People the <hi>Turks</hi> are, and that there's no reaſon to fear them.</p>
               <p>But apparently this Experience had been neglected, had not the <hi>Pope</hi> by his Entreaties, Liberalities, and zealous Care, oppoſed himſelf to the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (who are Neighbours to the <hi>Turks</hi>) always have, of entring into his Favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>Here's a great Obligation, for which <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is indebted to <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. and at the ſame time to <hi>Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha Baſſa.</hi> But if it be true, that the Death of this latter, may be regarded as diſadvantageous to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſeeing he was a Man who would have repaired one Extream by another that is worſe; yet it muſt be granted on another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, that it is advantageous to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> that the Cuſtom of ſtrangling the <hi>Grand Vizirs</hi> is come again in Faſhion. It was the <hi>Grand Vizir, Mehemmet Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruli,</hi> who Remonſtrated to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> (that is now depoſed) when he would raiſe him to this Firſt Place in
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152938:93"/> the Empire, That he could not act therein with Succeſs, in re-eſtabliſhing the Authority of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> which was a Prey at the frequent Changes of the <hi>Vizirs,</hi> if he let him not enjoy this Supreme Dignity to his Natural Death. The <hi>Sultan,</hi> who ſaw himſelf every day expoſed to Seditions, and in danger of loſing his Life, ſtuck not to receive a Propoſition, in which he was no leſs intereſſed than <hi>Mehemmet Kupruli;</hi> and his <hi>Highneſs</hi> found hereby ſuch benefit in a few Years, that he ever main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this Miniſter, and his Son (who Succeeded him in the ſame Poſt, though then but twenty ſeven years of Age) during their whole Lives. But we need ſay no more of <hi>Mehemmet Kupru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> of whom we have largely ſpoken elſewhere; and we have only mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus much now, to ſhew, That if the Conſervation of this Firſt Miniſter, and his Son likewiſe to their Deaths in the Government, had been ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, it is very probable, That <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Cara Muſtapha Baſſa</hi> to Death, terrified the ſucceeding <hi>Vizirs;</hi> as is effectually ſeen from the taking of <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:152938:93"/> in ſuffering modeſtly a Place of that conſequence to be taken before their Eyes, without daring to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard a Fight to hinder it, though they had a conſiderable freſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and come expreſly for this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another that was very weak, and diminiſh'd by a three Months Siege.</p>
               <p>This Cuſtom of getting rid of the <hi>Vizirs,</hi> having been ſuſpended for twenty Years, has been re-eſtabliſh'd, as a mark of the happy preparation, which has faln out on both ſides, by the Hand of <hi>God,</hi> in favour of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> There never was a more wiſh'd for Overture, to regain on the <hi>Turks</hi> what they took from the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> at leaſt in <hi>Europe;</hi> and it's certain, they may effect it in one Campaign more, if they attack theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> as vigorouſly as they ought to do.</p>
               <p>All the Neighbours of the <hi>Turks</hi> may expect great Progreſſes, if each one on his ſide does his endeavour: And, if the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> enter into <hi>Turky</hi> and <hi>Crimea,</hi> will they not then give a notable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to the <hi>Germans,</hi> to puſh on vigorouſly on their ſide, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152938:94"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:152938:94"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:152938:95"/> all <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> and the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as far as <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> now it lies open by the taking of <hi>Buda, Eſſeck</hi> and all <hi>Hungary?</hi> It is certain, (not to ſpeak of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the Inteſtine Rebellions which may happen) that if theſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian States,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Germans, Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Polanders,</hi> and <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeparately, and with Vigour, they will mutually aid one another, and do him more Prejudice, than if they acted together, and only on one ſide.</p>
               <p>To Crown the enterpriſe, its certain, That if the King of <hi>Poland</hi> does once advance to the Banks of the <hi>Danube,</hi> as he has almoſt already done, leaving behind him <hi>Caminiec,</hi> and ſome other Place of ſmall conſequence, carefully obſerved by flying Camps; there's not the leaſt Obſtacle, which can hinder his Armies always triumphing, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally over the <hi>Turks,</hi> from going to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If heretofore the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> have come by Sea and Land, ravaging and pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all along the Chanel, even Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs of the Imperial City, though the <hi>Port</hi> had Land and Sea-Armies
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:152938:95"/> againſt <hi>Poland;</hi> though ſhe had no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion otherwiſe, nor any inward Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and though ſhe was, in fine, in her higheſt point of Splendor, Power, and Riches; what may not the <hi>Poles</hi> do now by Land, and the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> at Sea, now the <hi>Turks</hi> are exhauſted of Men and Money, having almoſt none on this ſide, no more than elſewhere; and that the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who are the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark and Prop, are employed in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending their own Country againſt the <hi>Moſcovites?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But after all, ſhould the <hi>Venetians</hi> go directly to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> whether during theſe Projects were executed on the ſide of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> or even without this; its certain, that the only Fame of the march of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, and yet better of all at once, would cauſe an univerſal Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and be ſufficient to put the Land-Armies in Diſorder; whence may be concluded, what would happen, ſhould they deſtroy this great Town, as it is eaſy to do, as I have already ſhewed. They might find their reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning here; for, beſides the Booty, they might aſſure the Domination of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152938:96"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:152938:96"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:152938:97"/> the <hi>Mediterraneari</hi> and <hi>Archipelago,</hi> and conſequently, the retaking of <hi>Candia, Negropont,</hi> and all the Iſles.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> would fall under ſuch a rude and fatal Blow. He puts all his Strength in <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and if it be not really there, one may ſay, it's there by Reputation. This Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> is eſteemed ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in all the Empire, and there's thought ſuch a great impoſſibility to ſet on it, that all would ſeem loſt, ſhould it be ruined. The <hi>Sultan</hi> could not eſcape; for ſhould he ſteal away from the Victories of the <hi>Germans, Poles, Venetians,</hi> and <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> this muſt be by Flight, which would be travers'd by his own Subjects, by the <hi>Morlaques, Sclavonians,</hi> and ſo many others, who expect only the occaſion and aſſurance, that their Inſurrections ſhould be upheld. The <hi>Turks</hi> would repaſs the Sea, and abandon <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> with greater haſt than they took it; and his <hi>Highneſs</hi> would think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf happy were he permitted to make <hi>Burſa</hi> (the Capital of <hi>Aſia Minor</hi>) the Seat of his Empire; and, if in this other part of the World, he could be
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152938:97"/> freed from Rebellions and Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>It is well known, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. (the depoſed Emperor) was much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved by his People, as a Prince of great Goodneſs; and without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, the gentleſt of all who have preceded him. And who can tell what will be the Fate of his Brother <hi>Solyman</hi> now Reigning? For, the <hi>Turks</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves, that the good or bad ſucceſs of Affairs, depend on the good or bad Planet of him who manages them, therefore it is, that they willingly incline to the change of their Emperor.</p>
               <p>Theſe great and ſolid Conſiderations, would have paſs'd for <hi>Chimera's</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time, and one muſt have ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the executing of them, That the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> muſt have been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd in ſeveral Parts; That there being a firm League of all the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>States</hi> to his Countries, he will not have innumerable Armies, nor could oppoſe Two hundred thouſand men to each Prince who ſhould attack him; and that, on the contrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obliged to divide his Forces, he would have but mean ones againſt each
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152938:98"/> of his Enemies. But; O good God! Theſe Suppoſitions, are they not now certain and clear Truths as the day?</p>
               <p>If he was obliged to withdraw at the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> although he had all his Forces joined together, which yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted not to what was imagined; and, if ſince he has loſt his beſt Troops, Places, and all the Battels which have been fought; what will it be now; when he muſt ſtill more divide his Forces by reaſon of the <hi>Moſcovites?</hi> And it's apparently this Reaſon, which has obliged the ſage Policy of <hi>Venice,</hi> to carry her Arms to the end of the <hi>Peloponneſe,</hi> and as far ſhe can, to divert as much as may be, the Enemy from the Neighbourhood of her Eſtates.</p>
               <p>There could not happen to the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> a greater Good, than to ſee the King of <hi>Poland</hi> return again into <hi>Hungary;</hi> for, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inging himſelf on this ſide on the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, and the <hi>Germans</hi> relying on the <hi>Poles,</hi> whom they might have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the difficult Rencounters, the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army might have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaged <hi>Poland,</hi> which would have lain open.</p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:152938:98"/>
               <p>It will be demanded perhaps, Why the <hi>Turk</hi> ſent not Forces into this Kingdom, the firſt Campaign, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Siege of <hi>Vienna?</hi> but it's to be conſidered, that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> did not declare himſelf againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> till late, and though he had Sign'd the League with the Emperor, theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> were ſtill in hopes he would not execute it. Yet one may be perſwaded, they would not have done much Hurt to <hi>Poland,</hi> nor have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verprofited by the abſence of this Prince, eſpecially if the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> did their Duty; but it's probable, that his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> would omit the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of doing them much damage, and procuring himſelf as much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage on his ſide, as he has obtained for his Allies.</p>
               <p>If, in fine, the <hi>Port,</hi> which might have eaſily foreſeen the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his <hi>Poliſh</hi> Majeſty to ſuccour the Emperor, could not ſpare Forces to oppoſe him; If the <hi>Turks</hi> (ſo Powerful, according to the vulgar O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion) could not make the leaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment, to hinder the Paſſage of this Prince, and his joining the Imperial
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:152938:99"/> Troops; If they find themſelves under a Neceſſity of ſeeking now Peace from their Enemies, by reiterated Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, in ſuch a manner as ſtill ſhall be preſcribed them; and if again once more, they cannot ſhew any Body of an Army ſmall or great, which is not always beaten, whether in <hi>Hungary,</hi> the <hi>Morea, Daimatia,</hi> or in <hi>Poland,</hi> and on Sea; it's certain, that in opening only ones eyes, without great Penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a man may more and more diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Weakneſs and Ignorance of this Enemy which muſt be thought ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable.</p>
               <p>Not to mention the advantage from the <hi>Moldavians, Walachians, Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> which are Subſidiary Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, from whom there's no Benefit to be expected, but when the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſhall be ſtrongeſt. One may alſo in good Policy, not rely much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Precaution, on theſe <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who are half <hi>Mahometans;</hi> who readily ſubmit when they ſee a Power falling on them, which they cannot avold by Artifices; and who, if they be intereſted that the <hi>Infidels</hi> ſhould be mortified, ſeeing this ſuſpends the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:152938:99"/> Fines which are wont to be laid on them, and procures them good Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> yet are they more intereſted in the main, That the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power be not overthrown, by reaſon their particular Intereſt would be ſoon loſt in the Emperor, or King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems, as if the <hi>Turks</hi> had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered their Affairs politickly enough, in leaving theſe <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes on their Frontiers, and contenting themſelves with drawing a Tribute from 'em, and their Aſſiſtance. They indeed could not do otherwiſe in the beginning of their Conqueſts, but in the Sequel they might have erected theſe Provinces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Baſſa-ſhips,</hi> or Governments. But they choſe rather, to raiſe particular Perſons to theſe Principalities, or keep thoſe who were in Poſſeſſion of them; and they fail not to make known to thoſe Princes, when by grieving them they give them occaſion to complain, that without the Authority of the <hi>Port,</hi> they would not be in the Rank they are. The <hi>Grand Vizir, Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha Baſſa,</hi> could ſay to the <hi>Raguſians; What do you complain of? Would you not
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152938:100"/> have been long before now incorporated into the</hi> Venetian <hi>Territories, without the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of my Maſter? and inſtead of that You are Sovereigns, equal to other</hi> States <hi>of the Nations of the</hi> Meſſias.</p>
               <p>It's not thus with the <hi>Morlaques, Sclavonians,</hi> and <hi>Bulgarians.</hi> They ought to be held for Warlike People, which find no Oppoſition contrary to their Liberty, by the Intereſt of a particular Prince, and who for the moſt part are Exerciſed in the Art Military during the <hi>Venetian</hi> Wars. It remains now to ſpeak of the <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks,</hi> who are a bold, Warlike Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that can endure Labours; great Enemies of the <hi>Turks,</hi> but very much for their own Intereſt; They are to be conſidered as real Thieves, fit for Courſes and Pillages: Theſe are the <hi>Chriſtian Tartars,</hi> and conſequently ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uncapable of making Conqueſts; yet they may act profitably, whilſt the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> and <hi>Poles,</hi> ſhall apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to any important Enterpriſe, if they can be truſted.</p>
               <p>What comes from being denoted, lays open the diſadvantageous Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the <hi>Infidels;</hi> but though they
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152938:100"/> themſelves are perſwaded of this, yet they have ſtill hopes that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> will weary themſelves at length, and give over their Undertaking. They conſidered as a great Advantage for them, what paſs'd after the raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Vienna;</hi> for, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what has been already obſerved, they well conceived, that they had been loſt at that Bout, had they been pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued; and conſequently, whatever Diſpoſition, or Cuſtom they have of thanking God, as well in bad as good Fortune, yet were they in a manner certain of this Inference, <hi>That the</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>are incapable of profiting from the good Succeſſes which happen to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> Ottomans, <hi>ſeeing they then failed in that which was ſo eſſential to them, and, in all Probability, ſo eaſy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They alſo beheld the Conduct of the Emperor towards the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> with great Conſolation: for, although they acknowledge the Bravery of this latter, and that they fear him, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving felt conſiderable Effects of it; they perſwaded themſelves, that the Jealouſies between theſe two Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heads, during their Enterview at
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:152938:101"/> 
                  <hi>Vienna,</hi> and ſince, would produce ſome good Effect. They believed, that without this it would have been eaſie for the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to exterminate Count <hi>Teckely;</hi> and that according to the Vigilance, Activity, and indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable Cares, which all the World ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges in his Majeſty, to his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he would without Controverſie have preferred the Fatigues and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of remaining in the Winter ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to the ſweet Pleaſures of returning into his own Country; and, that this <hi>Monarch</hi> would have profited by the Rigour of a Seaſon, which the <hi>Poles</hi> ſuffer ſo eaſily, to retake the Courſe of the Victory, and extend his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> ingenuouſly acknowledge their Fear in this Occaſion; but that on the Advice of <hi>Teckley,</hi> and on their own Knowledge, they flattered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that theſe beginnings of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion among their Enemies would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed farther. They alſo thought, That the Emperor might engage the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to return into <hi>Hungary;</hi> and that to oblige him the more, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:152938:101"/> of <hi>Vienna</hi> did not much matter the Weakneſs of the <hi>German</hi> Troops on that ſide, nor the Diverſion which they imagined he would make elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. The <hi>Turks,</hi> in fine, whatever they had ſuffered from his <hi>Poliſh</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at the Defeat of <hi>Vienna,</hi> hoped and choſe rather to ſee him return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hungary,</hi> for the Reaſons already mentioned, than to remain in <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> learn'd moreover with Pleaſure, the Miſintelligence which reigned between the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Electors,</hi> and even amongſt the Princes, and Generals of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army. They built much on the ſmall Stock of Money his Imperial Majeſty had: They could never imagine that the <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> who are naturally ſworn Enemies of the <hi>Poles,</hi> could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves with them againſt the <hi>Port;</hi> being perſwaded on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that they ſhould profit by their Engagement to attack them, and war againſt them on their ancient Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. As to the <hi>Perſian,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Report which ran of his March againſt them, they hold themſelves at preſent in Safety, by reaſon of his
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:152938:102"/> ſmall Experience in War, by a Peace of near Fifty Years; and the ſenſual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in which the <hi>Sofi</hi> is plunged, which he may colour over with a Motive of his Religion. And as to the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> were in a manner aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red they would be modeſt, and not undertake any important Enterpriſe; That moſt of their Officers would think only of continuing the War, and raiſe Diſtaſts and Miſintelligences between the Auxiliary Tioops, and thoſe of the <hi>Republick,</hi> which would cauſe great Diſorders, as have ſeveral times hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; and, that at leaſt in the Iſles of which they ſhould be the Maſters, they would permit (as was practiſed during the War of <hi>Candia</hi>) the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to be raiſed for the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be to be preſum'd, that theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> flatter themſelves too much by theſe Imaginations, yet is it to be feared on the other hand, that ſome of them may be true. But in what manner ſoever this is, it cannot be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough repeated, That if the <hi>Turks</hi> are not conſtrained to forſake entirely what they poſſeſs in <hi>Europe,</hi> before a Peace
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152938:102"/> be granted them, 'tis purely the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Fault: And after ſo many Proofs which we have ſhew'd, let us conſider a little, before we finiſh this Diſcourſe, what Circumſtance of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs is neceſſary, to procure us ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py an Overture.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> undertakes a War againſt his own Intereſt, and the more Advantageous to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as it hinders them from entring into a War againſt one another. But a Man cannot enough reflect on the Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the Council of <hi>Vienna</hi> ſeem'd to have had, of renewing the Truce with the <hi>Port,</hi> even of a long time. The Appearances were ſo great, that I ſaw come, in leſs than Two Years, to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Adrianople,</hi> Four Agents from the Emperor, one after another, becauſe they died as ſoon as ever they arrived, on which the Policy of the <hi>Turks</hi> was ſuſpected, who would hereby retard this Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and terminate firſt the Affairs they had elſewhere; and the <hi>Sieur Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parara,</hi> who in the laſt place was ſent extraordinarily for this to the <hi>Port,</hi> gathered no other Fruit from this,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:152938:103"/> than that of ſeeing himſelf obliged to follow the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> and be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Ravages of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> where the <hi>Germans</hi> have been neceſſitated to blunt the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Arms. The one begins the War though he ought not to have undertook it, the other ſees himſelf engaged thereto maugre his Policy.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> comes to their Aſſiſtance with few Men, not having time to raiſe many, and the <hi>Turks</hi> fly, although they have more than an Hundred and thirty thouſand. It ſeem'd alſo, according to the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Preſumptions which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had in favour of theſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> that they might have return'd to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Campaign the more powerful by ſome great Effort, and more fill'd with Fury and Vengeance.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> to ſuccour them, engages himſelf in the War againſt the <hi>Infidels,</hi> in favour of thoſe who had been ſuſpected to have intended his hinderance to the Throne. This Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Monarch forſakes his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and expoſes his Sacred Perſon. He appears ill ſatisfied with <hi>Teckely,</hi>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:152938:103"/> and he becomes his Protector, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him an Accommodation. <hi>Germany</hi> cannot reduce this Malecontent, and ſhe will not receive him. She falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Miſintelligence on this Account with his Majeſty of <hi>Poland.</hi> This <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Lord becomes in a manner a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> writing to the <hi>Pope</hi> in a moſt judicious manner, and very vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of his Proceedings.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> engage in the League againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> with a Vigilance, and Addreſs ſo extraordinary, that they have as ſoon began Expeditions, as declared the War againſt theſe <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels;</hi> though their ſage Politicks and Reaſons of State, might have alledged ſome Difficulties, and cauſed ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays. The <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire thinks not of augmenting his Naval Army, but at the laſt Extremity; and yet, no leſs dreads the Maritime Force of this moſt ancient and illuſtrious <hi>Republick,</hi> than it admires with all the reſt of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, the ſolid and prudent Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which flow from their Councils and unimitable Policy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spain,</hi> notwithſtanding the Diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Weakneſſes of its Monarchy,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:152938:104"/> yet gives all poſſible Demonſtrations of its Good-Will, by remitting of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and raiſing of Troops; which ſhe permits to be done in her <hi>States,</hi> for the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and the Oppreſſion of the common Enemy.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> ſpares not the Churches Revenues, his own particular, and is imitated in his Zeal by ſeveral Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. His <hi>Holineſs</hi> has no other Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, nor other Family, than the Deſtruction of the common Enemy. Yet he ſees, that all this Money can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be employ'd as he would have it; that, the more he gives the more is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, though he deviſes all poſſible Means to remedy this Inconvenience, and ſends his Gallies.</p>
               <p>The great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> joins his Veſſels with them: He ſends a Regiment of a Thouſand Men, and a conſiderable Number of <hi>Knights</hi> of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and other illuſtrious Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, to make Deſcents; with great quantity of Bombs, Powder, Bullets, and other Munitions of War, at his own Charge. In a word, his ſerene Highneſs forgets nothing which is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to prove his Zeal againſt the <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:152938:104"/> I ſaw he held in the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi>'s Family a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> whoſe Advices were equally good, profitable, and important.</p>
               <p>The great Maſter of <hi>Malta,</hi> has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd himſelf, by a Bravery and Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity worthy of him, to come in Perſon againſt the <hi>Infidels.</hi> He has ſet out, with all ſpeed, the Gallies of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> He has thereunto added Veſſels, and a moſt important ſuper-Addition of <hi>Knights</hi> and Souldiers, whoſe Valour and undaunted Reſolutions are ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to the <hi>Turks</hi> in all Occaſions, and particularly at the Siege of <hi>Coron,</hi> and <hi>Napoli de Romania,</hi> and in all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feats of the <hi>Seraſquier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> by the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Vertues hereditary to him, and which he has extended ſo far theſe laſt Campaigns, does not deferr the aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning his own <hi>States,</hi> to tranſport himſelf in Perſon with all his Troops to this War. He contents not himſelf with ſending ſeveral times a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Quantity of Bombs, Bullets, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all ſorts of neceſſary Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:152938:105"/> and to entertain, at his own Charge, a moſt conſiderable Army; but moreover, expoſes his Perſon in all Occaſions and Perils, where Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is to be obtain'd.</p>
               <p>All concurs; in fine, to the Ruin of the <hi>Infidels.</hi> The <hi>Republick</hi> of <hi>Genoa,</hi> notwithſtanding her Loſſes, lends Two Gallies; and furniſhes proportionably what ſhe can, to denote her Piety and Zeal in this Encounter.</p>
               <p>The aſtoniſh'd <hi>Turks</hi> place now their Confidence in the Cuſtom of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> who uſually make little Profit of the good Succeſſes they obtain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. They hoped alſo they could make Peace to their Advantage, when the War was not favourable to them. But they are ſo miſtaken in this laſt Hope, that though ſome bad Politicians (which ſeem'd to deſire on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trouble in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of <hi>Germany</hi>) would have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore induced the Emperor to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate himſelf with the <hi>Port;</hi> we ought to preſume, that the Juſtice and Intereſt of his Imperial Majeſty, will
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:152938:105"/> not ſuffer him to adhere to Counſels of this Nature, nor to agree to any thing which may hinder the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of the glorious Exploits per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed under his Standards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:152938:106"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. A Recapitulation of ſeveral Reaſons of the approaching Overthrow of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire: With ſeveral Remarks upon the late Revolutions at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE ſatal Error of the <hi>Turks</hi> in this laſt Age, ſeems to have been their undermining the very Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own Government. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from all Accounts of the Riſe and Progreſs of <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> that much Power, but little Policy at firſt acquired, and till of late maintained their Dominion; that ſtrength of Arm and not of Reaſon, was their Excellency; and that what the Sword got them, the Sword kept for them. They have been the only Left-handed Men in Government, whoſe Play, ſo long as they kept to it, was never well known to any Adverſary; but now at laſt, that they are fallen to ſhifting of Hands, every body beats them. For in ſhort, the true ſtate of their Caſe is this; their Security as well as Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, lay wholly in their ability for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:152938:106"/> Atchievements: But the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Mahomet</hi> the laſt, (by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Creature <hi>Kupruli,</hi> who carried <hi>Candy</hi> by his Conduct from the <hi>Venetians</hi>) did what in him lay, to keep under the mutinous Order of the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> by taking care that their old ſevere Diſcipline ſhould be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and raw unexperienced Fellows ſhould be liſted into their Order; to the end, the Inſolence of that Order might never more be able to wreſt the Scepter out of their Soveraign's Hand, not dreaming they were the Glory and Support of his Throne, till the Defeat before <hi>Vienna</hi> ſhow'd him his Miſtake. Had the <hi>Port,</hi> inſtead of refining its Politicks, inſiſted on keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtricter to its old military Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: Had it, I ſay, not effeminated and diſarmed the <hi>Janizaries;</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd them with a glorious Courage for the enlarging the Bounds of their Empire, and ſo kept them employ'd, <hi>Mahomet</hi> might in this laſt War have advanced his Frontiers as far on this ſide <hi>Vienna,</hi> as now they are retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the other. Their little Skill in Affairs ſhow'd its ſelf remarkably
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:152938:107"/> this laſt Year, in hindring the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Retreat from <hi>Eſſeck;</hi> for whom, as a flying Enemy, they ought to have built a Bridge of Gold, and not, when the Flight came to their own turn, break down the Bridge, as they did, and ſo expoſe the ſhattered Army to the Fury of the Conqueror. But into what a Panick, but impolitick Fear, did their Fate put them, when they ſo cowardly abandoned <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> without daring firſt to ſpring thoſe Mines, which might have laid the whole Town in Ruins, when all was in readineſs, but a Hand to give fire to the Train. And, after all this, that the remainder of a broken Army ſhould ſet up a new General, <hi>Osman Hirsy,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Grand Vizir;</hi> and that to ſave himſelf, and ſtop the Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers, the <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> ſhould order the Bridge on the <hi>Save</hi> to be broken down, is an unparallell'd Inſtance of ill Conduct; Unleſs the Failure in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement appear more in theſe Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers ſawſy Behaviour to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, in butchering moſt of his great Officers of State, and in compleating their Villainy in depoſing him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:152938:107"/> he had at their Inſtance, retrenched his Expences, diſmiſs'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Domeſticks, ſacrificed moſt of his Friends and Favourites to their Rage, and then given their Eſtates to ſatisfy theſe Mutineers; which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently makes appear, how little ſafe it is for a Prince to comply with the unreaſonable Expectations of factious Subjects. And to add to the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Government, there appears a great Backwardneſs in the People to furniſh their Prince either with Men or Money; ſo that <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> ſeems in a fair way to be retaken by the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as it was firſt taken from them: For would, but the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who were very Rich, have contributed any thing to the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperor, their Soveraign, toward the keeping of that important Metropolis, when beſieged by the <hi>Turks,</hi> it might perhaps have been in <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Hands to this day: So, had the great Officers of the <hi>Port</hi> volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily given but a Third of thoſe Purſes which were by the mutinous Army taken from them, with their own Heads; the Army, in all likelihood,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:152938:108"/> might have been kept in Diſcipline and Obedience; and as many Towns won, as now, for want of Pay, and through their ungovernable Temper, they have quitted to the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> But how can it be expected that a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf can ſtand? How fatal Jealouſies between Prince and People are, the ſinking of this huge Empire proves.</p>
               <p>There is one thing more, which has been a great Abatement to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power; which is, their Averſeneſs to Arts, or to any thing that is Polite. For, let any one conſider what <hi>Greece</hi> did, while ſhe was Miſtreſs of the Arts; this one ſmall Part now of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, once atchieved more than all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Force was ever able to perform. The <hi>Perſians</hi> are at this day (in ſpite of the <hi>Turks</hi>) a potent King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who when they were Emperors of the Earth, ſubmitted to a <hi>Grecian</hi> Youth; and the whole Bravery of theſe new Inhabitants of <hi>Greece,</hi> with all their enlarged Territories, cannot e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual the Actions of either <hi>Sparta, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> or <hi>Macedon,</hi> much leſs the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Glory of all learned <hi>Greece.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:152938:108"/> I pray, their Weakneſs on this Account; whereas, it was the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of former barbarous Ages, to be the Conqueſt of either Civil <hi>Greece</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi> inſomuch that their Skill in Arts and all manner of Learning, invited Men to be their Subjects. I never yet heard any Man glory, that he was a Citizen of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> but have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten read, that the Freedom of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> was an invaluable Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo far has Learning the Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of Barbariſm.</p>
               <p>Nor is the Weakneſs of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Government leſs Conſpicuous in the Corruption of its Adminiſtrators: All Intereſts are meaſured by Profit, nor is it much matter, whom the Prince puts into Places of Truſt, ſince himſelf will be their Heir, ſaving, that there ſuch generally are pitch'd on, as know the beſt how to pillage the People; which has alſo taught the People how to take the like Meaſures; for, they never brook their Emperor's Commands, much longer than his Meaſures are ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in gratifying them with the Spoils of their Neighbours; ſo that all mutual Obligation between Prince
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:152938:109"/> and People, is there purely founded on Profit. As to Royal Goodneſs, or Subjects Duty, how little they are known now at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> let this laſt Revolution witneſs. No queſtion, but the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s greateſt Favourites led his Arms in this laſt, as well as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more fortunate Wars; yet not one Miscarriage by a General from the running from before <hi>Vienna,</hi> till this laſt Years return of the Rebels to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> coſt any thing leſs than loſs of Life and All. Who but an impotent Tyrant, would have abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Boſom-Friends to the heady Humour of the Multitude? He muſt certainly have been very regardleſs of his Intereſts, who would quit them ſo ſlightly to the Pretenſions of his Slaves. And the People ſhow'd their Prince the like Duty and Gratitude, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him, who in the former part of his Reign had brought under the <hi>Creſcent, Candia, Caminiec,</hi> and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Places in <hi>Hungary.</hi> Thus, when every body became greater than his Prince, as he had ſpared many of his Favourites Lives no longer than to tell where their Treaſures lay, the <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chites</hi>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:152938:109"/> beſtowed as many Baſtinado's on the Survivers, as did complete the Ruin of the Old Court. But, what a ſtrange Impotence in the Management of the Reins of his Government ſhow'd it ſelf, when the very <hi>Eunuchs</hi> could venture to oppoſe his Indignation; and the <hi>Boſtangi,</hi> or Gardiner, durſt refuſe to acknowledge his lawful Soveraign, and bid him look to his own Head, who demanded his for Rebellion.</p>
               <p>Their Divinity likewiſe is of equal Conſideration with their Politicks, which allows, that the Lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign may, for the good of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, be depoſed, and an Uſurper (for he can be no other) placed in the Throne: And this ſolemn Deciſion was paſs'd, by no leſs Man than the <hi>Mufti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Inconſtancy likewiſe to their old ſevere Maxims, in taking off all that might in any probability pretend to the Throne, ſhows the Inſtability of their Counſels, and the tottering Condition of the Government. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> it's true, ſhewed ſome weak Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the old Policy, when he would have concluded his Butcheries with
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:152938:110"/> his own Relations; but it proved too late: Yet (which is ſtill more ſtrange) the <hi>Mufti,</hi> who ſet up an Uſurper, durſt pronounce, that the lawful Prince, after he had denounced the Sentence of Depoſition upon him, ought to live. But, whether he may not live to give ſome of his Rebellious Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects their Deſerts, Time, and <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Succeſſes againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> muſt ſhow.</p>
               <p>One great Miſtake in this barbarous Polity, is, that all Men and their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings are meaſured altogether by their Succeſs, and not by the Rules of Prudence and Counſel. Whereas in <hi>Rome</hi> once a General puniſhed his Son, who had purchaſed a Victory by the Tranſgreſſion of his Orders: In this rough-hewen Government, the moſt unpolitick Actions, if but crowned with Succeſs, are accounted Brave and Glorious. Nor dare a Generaliſſimo for the wiſe <hi>Venetians,</hi> at this day pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue a Victory beyond his Maſters In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; for, ſhould he thereby gain <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> it ſelf, he would be ſo far from meriting by it, that the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would very much want a Pardon;
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:152938:110"/> ſuch a Value have all wiſe Men for a prudent Conduct in Affairs above the utmoſt Efforts of Courage and Brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. If the Reaſon of things ſwaied in <hi>Turky,</hi> little cauſe had that People to blame <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. for undertaking a War againſt the <hi>German</hi> Emperor, when Factions were ſo ſtrong on their Side in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the <hi>Germans</hi> were brought ſo low on the other by the Power of <hi>France.</hi> It is very ſtrange, that a People ſhould be ſo violently perſwaded of their Fate; and yet act as if there were no Providence. For, whoever drives on without prudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Conduct, muſt depend on a fortui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Hit, and can ſcarce do well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miracle; whereas, he that ſteers by Council, ſeems guided by the Clew of Providence, whither Fate has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined him. Certainly it is a ſtrange Defect in theſe Peoples Policy, to be ſo much ſwayed by Fortune, and ſo little by Counſel: For, grant but an Army to judge of their General by the Succeſs of a Battle; it muſt be left to their Diſcretion, whether they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him to a ſecond Engagement: Juſt thus has it fared with the <hi>Turks</hi> in
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:152938:111"/> this laſt War; it has not been the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion of <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. that has brought things to ſo low an Ebb, but it was the falſe Maxims of Policy, on which the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Government was founded. Where Arms are managed with a ſteady Hand, let the Succeſs be what it will, the Attempt is good; but once allow an Army to act beyond Commiſſion, though for the publick Good, that ſame Army, by virtue of the ſame Liberty, may act for the Subverſion of the Soveraign and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; of which this laſt Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> is a pregnant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152938:111"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
